<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The right of kings by Scripture, or, A collection of some Scriptures shewing kings to be of God also, An essay for orderly hearing : together with A defence of Psalm-singing : in several dialogues with their supposed speakers / by Joseph Bentham, once again rector of the Church of Broughton in Northhamptonshire.</title>
            <author>Bentham, Joseph, 1594?-1671.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 154 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 56 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27413</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13561257</idno>
  <idno type="VID">100286</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240859702</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1909A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R33777</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">13561257</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27413)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100286)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1561:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The right of kings by Scripture, or, A collection of some Scriptures shewing kings to be of God also, An essay for orderly hearing : together with A defence of Psalm-singing : in several dialogues with their supposed speakers / by Joseph Bentham, once again rector of the Church of Broughton in Northhamptonshire.</title>
                  <author>Bentham, Joseph, 1594?-1671.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 89 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E. C. for William Tompson, bookseller at Harborough in Leicestershire,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The right of kings by Scripture, or, A collection of some Scriptures shewing kings to be of God", "An essay for orderly hearing, dialogue-wise", and "A defence of Psalm-singing, dialogue-wise" each have special t.p.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Divine right of kings.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Church attendance.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Psalmody.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100286:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100286:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Right of KINGS by Scripture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>OR, A Collection of some Scriptures SHEWING Kings to be of God.</p>
            <p>ALSO, <hi>An Essay for Orderly Hearing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with, A Defence of Psalm-Singing.</p>
            <p>In several DIALOGUES With their supposed Speakers.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JOSEPH BENTHAM,</hi> Once again <hi>Rector</hi> of the Church of <hi>Broughton</hi> in <hi>Northamptonshire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>E. C.</hi> for <hi>William Tompson</hi> Bookseller at <hi>Harborough</hi> in <hi>Leicestershire.</hi> 1661.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:100286:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:100286:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THis little Treatise (such as it is) was pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned when our Martyr-King was living, but low. But passing from one Ministers hand to another, found it was in the study of one, who upon examination before a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee disclosed the Author; by which means, I lost my Copy: and (being known) feared to make it publick, as upon perswasions I intended. Which now I do, to shew the cause of mine and my Brethrens sufferings, namely, Conscience of our Duty; Loyalty
<pb facs="tcp:100286:3"/> to our King; Obedience to the Law of God, and the Land. At the beginning of our Troubles, I said, If the King and the Law stand, my Living will be mine; if the fall, I must fall with them: So I did. And through the mercy of God, by their restau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, I am (after seventeen years expulsion) in that Living again, which by the Law is my Freehold during life, I hope. My desire to you Brethren and Fathers, who have been fellow-sufferers, is, That as we formerly shewed much Patience, Courage, Cheerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and Constancy: So now, as much Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, Meekness, Forgetfulness of Injuries, forgiving of Wrongs: thereby evidencing our selves to be truly followers of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour and Soveraign; and that we did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure so much, and so long, only for Conscience sake, not for sini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ter or by respects. Yea, and that we think our selves well repayd, and to have preferment enough to see our King, our Countrey, and our Condition, so happy as now it is. And I beseech you, who were so long seated in our places; especially you who so much favour them as (for I think
<pb facs="tcp:100286:3"/> them to have more Reason and Religion than) to condemn us, complaining at our Re-admission; and bewailing their Removal from our Rights; to consider seriously our right, and theirs; our persons, and theirs. The same Law which gives you any thing you call your own, gives us what was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held so long from us. And as there are some who suffered with us, for whom we will not plead: so there were as able, as pious, as in-offensive, and painful Prelates, and Preachers, Masters, and Fellows of Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges outed, as the Christian World affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Do not, I humbly intreat you, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure at our returning, it being but to our just rights: and do not cry out of Cruelty, of Persecution, of our throwing out of good men, of hard usage, or the like; since they had as much favour as they could reasonably desire, and far more then they could expect, entring upon whole Crops, and departing with half; Arrears pardoned, and Dilapida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, in a manner forgiven. I am sure I had my Cattle driven away, four load of Goods taken away, with the losse of my Living;
<pb facs="tcp:100286:4"/> whereas these, none: We were Silenced, and disabled from every thing to which our Education fitted us; these are as free-men as others, for which I am glad, desiring that we and they may joyn as Brethren in Gods Work. I was also (so I believe there were more) outed Un-heard, Un-accused, not once Summoned to Answer, nor Articled against, until after almost three quarters of a year my Goods and Living were taken from me And the then Articles were such, which accused me of <hi>Loyalty:</hi> As, <hi>My being at the Commission of Array: My refusing to read the Books sent by the Parliament: My not paying Taxes without distraining: My affirming, That if the King had but one man with him, yet I would assist him:</hi> and, <hi>That I could alledge twenty Scriptures for the King, but none could be alledged for what the Parliament did: My disswading men from bringing Horse and Arms to the Parliament; alledging Scripture, and the practice of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Christians,</hi> &amp;c. Now that you may see that I and my fellow Sufferers had good ground for what we did, and suffered; this (although little) Discourse will evidence: so,
<pb facs="tcp:100286:4"/> as (I hope) to cleer us; and to convince you to joyn with us in <hi>Fearing God and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouring</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 24. 21.</note>
               <hi>our King, and no more to meddle with them who are given to change:</hi> which is the wish of him who</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Grege, fraude: <hi>Bello expulsus,</hi>
                  <date>July 14. 1643.</date>
               </dateline>
               <dateline>Rege, lege: <hi>Pace reversus,</hi>
                  <date>Septemb. 29. 1660.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Joseph Bentham.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:100286:5"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:100286:5"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Right of KINGS by Scripture.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>OR, A Collection of some Scriptures SHEWING Kings to be of God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>DIALOGƲE-WISE.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>IN WHICH</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>The supposed Speakers are
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>A new</hi> JUSTICE.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>An old</hi> PREACHER.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>A Sequestred</hi> DIVINE.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>By <hi>JOSEPH BENTHAM,</hi> Once again <hi>Rector</hi> of the Church of <hi>Broughton</hi> in <hi>Northamptonshire.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>E. C.</hi> for <hi>William Tompson</hi> Bookseller at <hi>Harborough</hi> in <hi>Leicestershire.</hi> 1661.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:100286:6"/>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:100286:6"/>
                  <head>To the READER.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Christian Reader,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Have so often of late, heard affirmed in such places, to such persons, and with such confidence, <hi>That no man can shew from Scripture, that Kings are of God; of his appointment:</hi> that I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded the misleading of some will, of others may, be imputed unto me, should I be wholly silent. The avoiding whereof, occasioned me, out of the abundance, to collect some Scriptures, to convince, if it may be, and recal such men from their groundless Conceipts; and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to stop the spreading of such strange Opinions. I have comfortably, I praise God, suffered, and still do, for my Loyalty to my King. And desiring to have the Church and Kingdom flourish, I do heartily wish, that men might know, and so do, their duty, tending to
<pb facs="tcp:100286:7"/> such good ends. That we would <hi>render to</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 7, 8.</note>
                     <hi>all their dues, tribute to whom tribute is due,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Owing nothing to any man but love.</hi> That the King may have his, and the People their right: Which being done, I doubt not, but peace and plenty shall be in, and upon our <hi>Israel.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>N. W. <date>1647.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Thine in the Lord,</hi>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="dialogue">
                  <pb facs="tcp:100286:7"/>
                  <head>THE Right of KINGS by Scripture, OR, A Collection of some Scriptures SHEWING KINGS to be of GOD.</head>
                  <p>In this Dialogue the supposed <hi>SPEAKERS</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Are
<list>
                        <item>A New JUSTICE.</item>
                        <item>An Old PREACHER.</item>
                        <item>A Sequestred DININE.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <div n="1" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. I.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                        <p>WEL met Sir: Methinks you look well and cheerfully notwithstanding the troubles which have befaln you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Div.</speaker>
                        <p>You know Sir, That <hi>Daniel</hi> with his pulse in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>d was fayrer of Countenance then others.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
                        <p>1. 15. And there is no cause why I should be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise then cheerful: God giving me such means, and living: an heart willingly at his call to leave them: and providing for me some friends, and subsistence where I come: that I have no cause of complaint, much of comfort, and praising God.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:100286:8"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:100286:8"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:100286:9"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:100286:9"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:100286:10"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:100286:10"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="2" facs="tcp:100286:11"/>
                        <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
                        <p>You may remember that I (having been your constant hearer) came to your Town and House: per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swading you to joyn with us; And to do as other God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Divines did, telling you it would else be worse with you: and you quickly saw my words come to passe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Div.</speaker>
                        <p>And you may also remember, that I told you, I knew your divines better then you: that if you could bring me from them, but one convincing Scripture, I was yours. Until then, you must give me leave to do according to my Conscience: that I must give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count to one greater then King, and Parliament: and therefore I wou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>d not go against my Conscience what ever befel me, yea although I should lose L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>berty, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and my Life. And as for that which befel me, I blesse God for the same: desiring him to give the Authors, and Actors repentance, and forgiveness for their unheard-of dealing, depriving me of my goods and living, not once heard to speak, nor once summo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to answer for my self.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
                        <p>I confesse you had hard measure. But now being thus happily met, I pray you tell me what you think of Kings, some men affirming that Kings are but like other men, that they are not of Gods appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and with such confidence that I my self am now of the same opinion.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Div.</speaker>
                        <p>Truely Sir, you might have met with many bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter furnished, to have resolved you then my self, who have had such usage from you, and your agents, That my study door was once broken open: another time locked up: some of my books sold about the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey: and my self forced to such a condition, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years I was deprived of the remainder of my Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brary,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:100286:11"/> yet I will not refuse to answer your demand: and I hope resolve you if Scripture may take place.</p>
                        <p>First, Whereas you say, what are Kings more then other men? Let me I pray ask you, what are you more then another man. Yet in the relation of Father, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, Justice, (supposing your commission to be deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from a right fountain) I know you are above your Children, servants, and neighbors. Take heed of such kind of reasonings, lest your own darts retort back against you in your, and all superiours, in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations. What you will say against Kings, may be said against Lords, Gentlemen, Masters, and Fathers. Strike Authority in the head it will languish in the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. Take heed of opening the Sea-banks, which are not easily stopped. And you know <hi>who puts the tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults, or madnesse of the people; with the noise of the Seas and of their waves,</hi> Psal. 65. 7.</p>
                        <p>Again, are not our High ways, and Laws, called the Kings? and people, his Subjects? Do not Commissions come forth in his Name? Are not Inditements against offenders Forasmuch as against the peace of our Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Lord the King? Are not our Judges, Justices, She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffs, and Constables sworn as the King? Are not Parl. called by the Kings writ? &amp; doth not this sit by his Act?</p>
                        <p>Moreover should I ask you, If any order of men are of God? You will answer, yes, as Fathers, Masters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Then be advised, and you shall see as ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>y, if not more Scriptures to shew Kings to be of Gods appointment. And not more to be objected against Kings in Scripture, then against such. And whereas in Scripture it is no where said, <hi>Call no man King on Earth,</hi> yet in it our Saviour saith, <hi>Call no man Master, or Father on Earth. Matth.</hi> 23. 9,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100286:12"/> 10. Which I know is not so to be understood, but that I may comfortably expect honour and the name of Father, from the Children God in mercy hath given me: and might from my servants, the name (until you disabled me from being in the relation of a Master. And truly Sir, It is a wonder to me, if any, who rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>cripture attentively, doth not heartily, and without scruple acknowledge that Kings are of God. For although Kings are but men, yet they are such men, <hi>Who are the light of Israel,</hi> 2 Kin. 8. 19. <hi>And who are worth thousands of others.</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18. 3.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
                        <p>Cease to wonder. For I my self am a reader of scripture: and they who drew me to this opinion pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend much to scr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>pture. Let me therefore hear wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> you can say from Scripture: for your word is not so.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Div.</speaker>
                        <p>Agreed: And for method and memory sake, I will set down those Scriptures, I can with so little help collect, in four heads. All which will shew that Kings are of God.</p>
                        <p>
                           <list>
                              <item>The first from cleer texts of Scripture, shewing they are of God.</item>
                              <item>The second from diverse promises to, and concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; Kings.</item>
                              <item>The third from examples of Kings good, and bad.</item>
                              <item>The fourth from duties enjoyned by God, for, and to, Kings.</item>
                           </list>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:100286:12"/>
                     <head>CHAP. II.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
                        <p>Come to your first ground.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Div.</speaker>
                        <p>I will, and shew you that the Scripture doth precisely, and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ively manifest Kings to be of God. Prov. 8. 15. The Lord saith, <hi>By me Kings raign. By me:</hi> As invested with his power from above by him they raign, so that their commands, and authority are by Him. This place is blundered at by some men to lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle purpose, since the <hi>Syriack</hi> reads it for me, the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew</hi> in me, both shewing that by the Authority of God all the authority of the earth hath force, and power, and from him it is derived It is the tenure of some men to hold their lands in chief, from the King immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately: but it is the tenure of Kings, to hold their crowns in chief, from the chief Lord of Heaven, and Earth. Hear <hi>Deodate.</hi> By me. <hi>I the eternal Son of God who am the Fathers subsisting wisdome,</hi> Prov. 1. 20. <hi>and supream Lord of the world, do appoint Kings, and Princes by such ways, and means as I please. They all have their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and power from mee, as my servants and deputies.</hi> It is God who pulleth down and setteth up <hi>Psal.</hi> 75. 7. <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. 15. <hi>He was to be King, whom the Lord should choose.</hi> Therefore they are originally, and immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately from God.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                        <p>That place in <hi>Deuterenomy</hi> makes against you for the words are, <hi>Thou shalt in any wise set.</hi> Therefore although the election of the person is Gods, yet the constitution of the person elected is the peoples.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="6" facs="tcp:100286:13"/>
                        <speaker>Div.</speaker>
                        <p>Those words, <hi>Thou shalt set</hi> are not meant of constitution by transferring from them Majesty, and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty to the King, but of constitution by the way of approbation and of accepting: acknowledging, reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rencing, and obeying as King, whom God constituted to be King. So 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 2. <hi>Saints are said to judg the wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ld,</hi> by approving, consenting, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                        <p>This is but your interpretation.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Div.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Deodate</hi> saith, <hi>Thou shalt acknowledg, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stal him, whom God shall point out by expresse declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ll.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Secondly, Practice is a good interpreter of the Law, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 9. 17. <hi>The Lord said, this same shal ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>gn.</hi> 10. 1, <hi>The Lord hath annointed thee,</hi> 13, 13. <hi>The Lord hath set a King over you.</hi> God chose, the people admitted, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted. 16. 1. <hi>I have previded me a King saith God. Psal.</hi> 89. 19, 20. <hi>I have exalted one chosen out of the people. I have found</hi> David. It was not the people nor the rulers of Bethlehem, nor <hi>Samuel</hi> the Prophet; but the Lord who found, who exalted.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly consider that all royall Acts of Kings are of God ascribed to him.</p>
                        <p>Their Crowning is from God; <hi>Psal.</hi> 21. 3. <hi>Thou hast set a Crown of pure Gold on his head.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Their annointing is by the Lord, <hi>Psal.</hi> 89. 20. <hi>With my Holy oyl, have I annointed him.</hi> The oyl is called as <hi>Gods?</hi> So <hi>Sacred.</hi> Being from a Sacred fountain and efficient God: and having a Sacred influence on the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons making them Sacred in some sort.</p>
                        <p>Their thrones are Gods. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29. 23. <hi>Solomon sate on the Throne of the Lord as King,</hi> which Throne is called <hi>the Throne of the Kingdome.</hi> 1 Kin. 1. 46. and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100286:13"/>
                           <hi>of David.</hi> v. 48. <hi>Their Judges judge for the Lord.</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19. 6.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>It is the Lord who girds them with strength,</hi> Psal. 18. 39. <hi>Their losse of power is from God,</hi> 2 Chron. 36. 23. <hi>God gave</hi> Cyrus <hi>all the Kingdomes of the Earth.</hi> Ez. 1, 2. Isa. 45. 1 Dan. 2. 21. <hi>He removeth Kings,</hi> Dan. 4. 17. <hi>The most high ruleth,</hi> v. 25. <hi>He divides and gives Kingdomes,</hi> Dan. 5. 20. <hi>It is he who looseth the bonds of Kings,</hi> Job. 12. 18. <hi>and who casteth their Crowns to the grou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>d▪</hi> Psa. 8<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. 44.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>And wrongs to Kings are done to God,</hi> Rom. 13. 4. <hi>Whosoever resisteth, resist<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>h the Ordinance of God.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                        <p>I am glad, you mention that place in the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> which is oft alledged, but it never mentions K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ngs: only powers, and the higher power.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Div.</speaker>
                        <p>This place doth expresly prove the thing in question. <hi>v.</hi> 1. <hi>There is no power but of God. The pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers that be, are ordained of God.</hi> He is the Author of them. v. 2. <hi>Whosoever resisteth the power, resisteth the ordinance of God.</hi> Mark, <hi>Of God, ordained of God, Ordinance of God,</hi> after called <hi>the Minister of God. v.</hi> 4, 6. And this Epistle was written to the <hi>Romans,</hi> when at <hi>Rome</hi> such monsters of men as <hi>Nero,</hi> and <hi>Caligula</hi> were Emperors: which persons clothed with Soveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty are said to be of, by, or from <hi>God immediately.</hi> And to them subjection was enjoyned.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                        <p>Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nt <hi>Peter calls them the Ordinance of Man,</hi> 1 Pet. 2. 13.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Div.</speaker>
                        <p>That which St. <hi>Peter</hi> calls the Ordinance of man. v. 15. <hi>he calls the will of God, and Saint</hi> Paul <hi>the Ordinance of God.</hi> Rom. 13. 2.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Are vicious Kings of God?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="8" facs="tcp:100286:14"/>
                        <speaker>Div.</speaker>
                        <p>Although some such persons are vitious, and evil: yet the order, and ordinance is Gods, and good; our Saviour acknowledged <hi>Pilates</hi> power who condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him to be of God, <hi>Joh.</hi> 19. 11.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                        <p>The Prophet saith, <hi>God gave them a King in his Anger, Hos.</hi> 13. 11.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Div.</speaker>
                        <p>True, and that he took him away in his wrath. Where observe, <hi>That to have a bad King is of God:</hi> a chastisement of an angry God. That to have an evil King unking'd, is of God also. He only makes and he on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unmakes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
                        <p>But in <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>muel</hi> we see, <hi>The first King the Iews had, was desired by them:</hi> and of <hi>Samuel</hi> who was dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleased thereat, and the Lord was so far forth displea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, that he saith, They had rejected him, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8. 5, 6, 7. and it is said, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>hat the people made him, chose him, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11. 15. 8. 5.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Div.</speaker>
                        <p>First, <hi>Saul was not the first King, for Moses was King;</hi> Deut. 33. 5. <hi>and the Iudges were as Kings, I think.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Secondly, They desired a King, but did not appoint or choose: only submitted to <hi>Saul,</hi> whom God gave them, <hi>shooting, and saying, God save the King.</hi> 1 Sam. 10. 24. The people indeed desired one, <hi>God gave them Saul.</hi> Act. 13. 21.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>God sent him, I will send thee a man,</hi> 1 Sam: 9. 16.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>God shewed him to Samuel;</hi> 1 Sam. 9. 17.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>God chose him,</hi> 1 Sam. 10. 24.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>God found him,</hi> 1 Sam. 10. 21, 22.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>God anointed him,</hi> 1 Sam. 10. 1.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Saul w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap> made a King, confirmed a King by signs,</hi> 1 Sam. 10. 2, 3. <hi>and executed his office of a King.</hi> 1 Sam.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:100286:14"/> 11. 7, 8. before it is said, The people made him King. <hi>v.</hi> 15.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
                        <p>What was their making then?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Div.</speaker>
                        <p>Nothing but an approving &amp; applauding him, <hi>whom God had made King</hi> 1 Sam. 10. 24. <hi>so God found David,</hi> Psal. 89. 20. <hi>and exalted him,</hi> v. 26. <hi>Choice, and exaltation, both of God.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
                        <p>Why was God then displeased with them.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Div.</speaker>
                        <p>Not for desiring of a King, but for,</p>
                        <p>Their diffidence relying on men, more then God.</p>
                        <p>Their boldnesse; and presumption, desiring of themselves to erect a new form of Government.</p>
                        <p>Their contempt of Gods ordinance.</p>
                        <p>Summe up what is said, and see. <hi>By the Lord Kings raign.</hi> It is he who sets them up, it is he who chooseth them. Their crowning, anointing, thrones, and judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are his. It is he who girds them with strength, wrongs done to them, are done to him, their losse of power is from him, they are his ordinance, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is cleer they are from God; And somewhat more manifest it will be to us if we consider that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture doth give so much more then ordinary power to Kings, that it saith as followeth, Job. 34. 18. <hi>Is it fit to say to a King, thou art wicked?</hi> shewing, from the respect which is due to earthly Princes, <hi>the Reverence which is due to God,</hi> Prov. 30. 31. <hi>A King against whom is no rising up,</hi> Eccles. 8. 4. <hi>Where the word of a King is, there is power, and who may say unto him, what dost thou?</hi> Prov. 16. 14. <hi>The Kings wrath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                                 <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                              </gap> the messengers of death,</hi> Prov. 19. 12. <hi>As the r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                                 <desc>•••</desc>
                              </gap>ing of a Lyon</hi> 20. 2. <hi>So is his fear,</hi> 20. 8. <hi>A Ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>g <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>hat sit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in the Throne of Iudgment scattere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>h away <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>vil</hi>
                           <pb n="10" facs="tcp:100286:15"/>
                           <hi>with his eyes.</hi> v. 26. <hi>A wise King scattereth the wicked.</hi> God having imparted to them, such power, and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, they are certainly of God.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. III.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
                        <p>COme to your second ground you mention'd, and shew from Scripture, that Kings are of God from promises.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Div.</speaker>
                        <p>Very willingly. These promises proving the point; are of diverse sorts. God promised to <hi>Abraham▪ Gen.</hi> 17. 6. and to <hi>Sarah</hi> 16. As a Mercy to them, <hi>that Kings should come out of them.</hi> To <hi>Judah</hi> the <hi>Scepter, Gen.</hi> 49. 10. and to <hi>Israel, that his King should be higher then Agag, Numb.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. 7.</p>
                        <p>It is one of Gods mercies to prosper into a Kingdom <hi>Ezech.</hi> 16. 13. and to have the shout of a King amongst a p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ople. <hi>Numb</hi> 23. 21. It is a mercy to have one King <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zech.</hi> 37. 22. one King shal be King to them all, whereas for the transgressions of a Land many are the Princes thereof, <hi>Pro.</hi> 28. 2.</p>
                        <p>It is an ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>raordinary mercy to have a good King, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 2. 11. because the Lord loved his people, he hath made thee King 9. 8. because the Lord loved <hi>Israel</hi> he made thee King over them.</p>
                        <p>God promised in mercy to give Kings to be nursing Fathers, &amp; Queens to be nursing Mothers to his Church <hi>Isa.</hi> 49. 23. and that they should suck the breasts of Kings, <hi>Isa.</hi> 60. 16.</p>
                        <p>He promised the <hi>Jews,</hi> that if they would sanctifie the Sabbath day, he would give them▪ Kings on the Throne of <hi>David, Jerem:</hi> 17. 25. So likewise if they would execute judgment, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 22. 4.</p>
                        <p>The Scriptures shew that Kings are a furtherance to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100286:15"/> peace, quietnesse, and godlinesse. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 1, 2.</p>
                        <p>The Lord hath promised, by Kings to destroy <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lon, Rev.</hi> 17. 16. the ten horns shall make her desolate and the ten horns are ten Kings, <hi>v.</hi> 12.</p>
                        <p>God hath promised to give victory to Kings, <hi>Psal.</hi> 144. 10. and answerably he subdued people under <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> v. 2. he delivered him from the hurtful sword, <hi>v.</hi> 10. and from the strivings of the people, <hi>Psal.</hi> 18. 43. And the Sciptures shew the great miseries that be in the want of a King?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
                        <p>What Scriptures shew the miseries in the want of a King.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Div.</speaker>
                        <p>Four times in <hi>Judges</hi> it is said, The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e was no King in <hi>Israel.</hi> 17. 6. 18. 1. 19. 1. 21. 25. Which occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioned those mischiefs by that great man <hi>Micah.</hi> The Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Gibeah</hi> &amp; the Tribe of <hi>Dan.</hi> When these Idolatries, rapines, and rapes abounded it is said, <hi>There was no King in Israel.</hi> Some thought it perhaps a merry world, when every one might do what he listed. But wanting a King they were in the way to ruin. So that better any one, then every one. A Judgment it is then to have no King in <hi>Isr.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>It is also threatned as a judgment to <hi>Israel</hi> to abide without a King, <hi>Hos.</hi> 3. 4. and amongst <hi>Jeremies La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations</hi> this is one, Her King and Princes are among the Gentiles, <hi>Lam.</hi> 2. 9.</p>
                        <p>The Holy Ghost saith moreover. The Jews shall say, we have no King because we fear not God, <hi>Hos.</hi> 10. 3. and threatneth that they should abide without a King, <hi>Hos.</hi> 3. 4. <hi>Mic.</hi> 4. 9. Why dost thou cry out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loud? is there no King in thee? <hi>Hos.</hi> 10. 7. as for <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria</hi> her King is cut off <hi>Zach.</hi> 9. 5. The King shall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish from <hi>Gaza.</hi> These a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>d such like are. I hope, suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient evidences, that Kings are of God. For, are Kings
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100286:16"/> promised as a blessing to people? to Nations? as fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to the Church? as an encouragement to holiness? Are such mercies promised to Kings? Is it a Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to want, and to be deprived of such? yea a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment, for not fearing of God? Then certainly such are of God.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. IIII.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
                        <p>VVEll, let me hear what Examples you bring from Scripture to shew that Kings are of God.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Div.</speaker>
                        <p>Examples of all sorts.</p>
                        <p>First I will give Examples of good Kings.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Melchisedeck</hi> King of righteousnesse, King of peace. <hi>Gen.</hi> 14. 18. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 1. 2. The first good King so cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s said to be without Father, and Mother, to shew, as some say, that the Generation of Kings is of God. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 3.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Moses</hi> was King in <hi>Jesurun, Deut.</hi> 33. 5. which was objected against him. <hi>Numb.</hi> 16. 13. <hi>He was of God, Exod.</hi> 3. 10. <hi>Psal.</hi> 77. 20.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>David</hi> was chosen of God, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6. 21. The Lord chose mee. 7, 8. <hi>I took thee saith God to be Ruler,</hi> 1 <hi>Chr.</hi> 10. 14. The Lord turned the Kingdome to <hi>David.</hi> 28, 4. The Lord chose me. He is therefore called Gods King, <hi>Psal.</hi> 18. 50. and Gods annointed, 20. 6. 98. 70. 89. 20. <hi>Salomon,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7. 12. 13. I will set up; saith God, thy seed after thee. 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 2. 18. The Kingdome is his from the Lord, 9. 5. I will establish the Throne of thy Kingdome, saith God, 1 Chron. 28. 5. Of my Sons, the Lord hath chosen <hi>Salomon,</hi> saith <hi>David.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <pb n="13" facs="tcp:100286:16"/>
                        <p> Secondly I will give some instances of the call of Kings. <hi>Saul was of God,</hi> 1 Sam. 10. 1. <hi>called Gods anointed,</hi> 1 Sam. 12. 3. 3.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Jeroboam of God,</hi> 1 Kin. 11. 35. 37. 12. 24.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Baasha of God,</hi> 1 Kin. 16. 2.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Jehu of God,</hi> 2 King. 9. 6. 10. 30.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly, I will give some examples of Heathen Kings.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Hazael of God,</hi> 2 Kin. 8. 13.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Nebuchadnezzar of God,</hi> Jer. 27. 6. Dan. 2. 37. 5. 18.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Cyrus of God,</hi> Isa. 44. 28. <hi>Cyrus</hi> my Shepherd, Isa. 45. 1.</p>
                        <p>Gods anointed, Annointed King includes a Title; excludes Usurpation; gives the admistration to govern, not the guift to govern well. The right of ruling, not of ruling rightly, for if Religion was that, that did the deed, Then <hi>Cyrus</hi> had not been the Lords anointed. If Vertue, then not <hi>Saul.</hi> If grace, neither a <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> without Wisdome; A <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> without Religion; An <hi>Hazael</hi> without pitty, were of God, of Gods sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and setting up. Kings therefore are of God.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. V.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
                        <p>VVHat is your fourth, and last ground from Scripture?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Div.</speaker>
                        <p>This, that God in his word prescribes duties to be performed by and to Kings, as to such sorts of men he appoints, and approves of.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                        <p>Doth the Scripture enjoyn duties for Kings to do?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Div.</speaker>
                        <p>It doth, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. 17. 16. 19. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 44. 3. 46. 2. 8, 16, 17, 18.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="14" facs="tcp:100286:17"/>
                        <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
                        <p>And what duties do Subjects owe to Kings in Scripture?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Div.</speaker>
                        <p>Duties of two sorts <hi>Negative, Affirmative.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>First the Scripture shews such negative duties, or, what Subjects may not do to their Kings as follows,</p>
                        <p>They may not despise them: for they are called Sons of <hi>Belial,</hi> who despised Saul, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10. 27. and walkers after the flesh, who despise dominion, 2 Pet. 2. 10.</p>
                        <p>They may not speak evil of them, <hi>Exod.</hi> 22. 28. Saint <hi>Iude</hi> calling such filthy dreamers who speak evil of dignities, <hi>Iud.</hi> 8. <hi>Miriam</hi> punished with Leprosy for not being afraid to speak against <hi>Moses, Numb.</hi> 12. 8. 10. and <hi>Naboth</hi> must be stoned for blaspheming God and the King, as they falsly witnessed, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 21. 13. In particular they may <hi>not curse</hi> the King, no not in their thought <hi>Eccles.</hi> 10. 20. <hi>Nor slander</hi> Psal. 89. 51. They, i. e. Thine enemies, O Lord, have reproached the footsteps of thine anointed. <hi>Nor revile,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6. 23. <hi>Michal</hi> for so doing, made childlesse.</p>
                        <p>They may not rule over them, <hi>Prov.</hi> 19. 10. It is not seemly for servants to have rule over Princes.</p>
                        <p>They may not touch. i. e. to their hurt, or prejudice, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16. 22. Touch not mine anoynted.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh Sir, I have looked for that place, Touch not mine annointed, so much urged by <hi>Royalists,</hi> which place makes much against you there, and <hi>Psal</hi> 105. 14. 15. for it is said, he reproved Kings for their sakes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Div.</speaker>
                        <p>Good Sir. Be not over confident, but consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</p>
                        <p>First, that that place is literally meant of <hi>Abraham, Isa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ac,</hi> and <hi>Iacob,</hi> there named, and makes nothing against Kings, but much for them. He reproved Kings for their
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100286:17"/> sakes, for whose sakes? <hi>Abrahams, Isaacks, and Iacobs,</hi> what Kings? <hi>Abimelech</hi> King of <hi>Gerar</hi> for <hi>Abrahams, Gen.</hi> 20. 3. also <hi>Pharach</hi> King of <hi>Egypt,</hi> 12. 7, <hi>Abime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lech</hi> King of <hi>Gerar</hi> for <hi>Isaacks Gen.</hi> 26. <hi>Heathen Kings, for Godly Kings.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>And these, for whom those Kings were reproved; were the supream Magistrates in the Church. All the Rulers Gods people then had. And <hi>Abraham</hi> was a mighty Prince, <hi>Gen.</hi> 23. 6. Yea such who conquered four Kings at once <hi>Gen.</hi> 14. <hi>Isaack</hi> was more mighty then <hi>Abimelech</hi> King of <hi>Gerar, Gen.</hi> 26. 16. who there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore made a Covenant, and League with him, <hi>v.</hi> 28. And <hi>Jacob</hi> was a Conquerour of the <hi>Amorite, Gen.</hi> 48. 22.</p>
                        <p>Secondly these were Patriarchs. And a Patriarch was the head of a Nation. So is <hi>Abraham</hi> called <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 4. So is <hi>David the King</hi> called; <hi>Act.</hi> 2. 29. Little difference, there is, if any between a <hi>King,</hi> and a <hi>Patriarch.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Thirdly, This is a considerable thing: That although in Scripture, there are who are said to be annointed as Priests, and Prophets. To have received an annoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as Saints; 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2. 20. Yet I am perswaded you cannot find in all the Scripture, any who are called Gods anointed but only Christ, <hi>Luk.</hi> 2. 26. &amp; Kings who are called Gods anointed above thirty times, never the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples anointed. For example, <hi>David</hi> is so called, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19. 21. <hi>Salomon,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16. 42. <hi>Josiah, Lam.</hi> 42. 20. <hi>Cyrus, Isa.</hi> 45. 1. and <hi>Saul</hi> thrice in two verses, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24. 5. 10. four times, 26. 9, 11, 16, 23. and twice, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1. 14, 16. And being Gods anointed, <hi>Davids</hi> heart smote him, for but cutting off his garment, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24. 5. Neither would he suffer any to stretch forth an hand against him, <hi>v.</hi> 7. Yet was <hi>Saul</hi> not only an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:100286:18"/> enemy against <hi>David,</hi> but also.</p>
                        <p>An Usuper of the Priests office, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13. 9.</p>
                        <p>A persecutor shedding the bloud of the High Priest, and fourscore and four of the Lords priests more, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22. 18.</p>
                        <p>One possessed with an evil spirit, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16. 14.</p>
                        <p>One rebellious against God, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. 23.</p>
                        <p>Tyrannical to men; for upon every sleight occasion up goes his <hi>javelin</hi> to smite, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14. 18. &amp; 11. 20. 33.</p>
                        <p>And a seeker to one who had a familiar spirit, 1 <hi>Chro.</hi> 10. 13. Yet being the Lords anointed, not to be tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
                        <p>Is there any other negative duty?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Div.</speaker>
                        <p>I will name one more, which is this. They may not resist, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 2. Yet <hi>Nero</hi> was the power to whom these were then Subject. Nor can we find, that ever <hi>Samuel, Elijab,</hi> or other Prophet, did stir up: or that the people did resist <hi>David,</hi> when an Adulterer; <hi>Solomon,</hi> when an Idolater; <hi>Saul, Ahab,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
                        <p>Some say, That Christians did not resist, and in the primitive times they might not resist, because they wanted power: It was in regard of their weakness, not unwillingnesse.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Div.</speaker>
                        <p>We read not of any resistance by Christ, any of his Apostles, nor of any Christians in the primitive times, withstanding the rage of persecutors, which did not arise from their weaknesse, as we may see, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26. 53. <hi>Act.</hi> 5. 19, 20, 23, 26. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 12. 8, 9 also in <hi>Cyprian,</hi> and <hi>Tertullian.</hi> And at <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>lians</hi> death the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my cryed out to <hi>lovinian,</hi> we are all Christians.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, This is a most uncharitable sentence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the holy Saints of God: as if they belyed the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:100286:18"/> thoughts of their hearts: proclaiming that is contrary to the Wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>d.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly, how injurious is this to the Holy Ghost? As if the Holy Ghost dejected accord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ng to the necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of times: not according to the equity of the thing. As if the Holy Ghost was a time-server. <hi>Monstrum hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendum.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>It was not therefore disability, but duty; not want of strength, but a reve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>end regard of the Lords annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, which wrought such effects in Christians.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
                        <p>But remember the Holy Ghost saith, <hi>They shall bind their Kings in chains,</hi> Psa. 149. 8.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Div.</speaker>
                        <p>But what Kings? <hi>Their Kings,</hi> namely, Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Kings, not their own, not Christian, not godly Kings.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, You never read of this literally fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly, those allegorical expressions shew the effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy of the spiritual sword of Gods word, by which Gods messengers should convert, and so offer in sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to God such great ones, who before were enemies to the Church, or make them inexcusable. Not that Saints should resist, or bind their Kings in bonds. For we must not think we are to neglect plain duties of subje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and obedience, upon the strength of an obscure prophesie.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
                        <p>But we read of resistance, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 12. 18. And it is said to be of God, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 14. 7. 12. 15.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Div.</speaker>
                        <p>1 <hi>King.</hi> 12. 18. proves it was done: not that it was well done, for the Scripture blames him, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 11. 26. The fact is called Rebellion, and the people Sonns of <hi>Belial,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 13. 6, 7. 10. 19. You may moreover observe this, That with their revolt, their
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100286:19"/> glory and happinesse departed. They became Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Worshippers of the calves, (and sometimes of <hi>Baal)</hi> at <hi>Dan,</hi> and <hi>Bersheba,</hi> they were promoters of the lowest of the people, to the Priests office: They were in continual Civil Wars, setting up, and pulling down (according as parties, and factions prevailed) Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers over them. And they were led away into captivity long before their brethren of <hi>Judah;</hi> nor ever returned back as they did. You cannot therefore conclude this act was justifiable because it proceeded from an evil fountain, a rebellious and impatient mind in them: having no order from God, thus to doe: although he had shewed by his Prophet, that thus it should be. For how displeasing this was to God, may be seen in that they were left alwaies under the government of Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Kings until destroyed, or faln into the hands of forraign enemies.</p>
                        <p>That place which shews it was of God, shews that the Lord suffered such a thing to be done as a punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for <hi>Solomons</hi> Idolatry. Neither approving their Rebellion, nor <hi>Rehoboams</hi> answer, so much as some i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine. Their complaint being causelesse, for they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver lived happier then in <hi>Solomons</hi> daies, in which</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>They were very populous,</hi> 1 King. 4. 20.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>They lived merrily, and joyfully,</hi> v. 16.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>They were much honoured, v.</hi> 21.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>They lived peaceably under their own vines, &amp;c.</hi> ver. 24. 25.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>They had much trading,</hi> 1 Ki. 10, 15.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>They had a brave fleet,</hi> 1 Ki. 9. 26, 28. &amp; 10. 22.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>They had plenty of silver, and gold,</hi> 2 Chron. 9. 20. 1 King 10. 27.</p>
                        <pb n="19" facs="tcp:100286:19"/>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Their happinesse was general from Dan,</hi> &amp;c. 1 King. 4. 24.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>And continued all his daies,</hi> v. 16.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh Sir, I have now catcht you. You say, 1 <hi>Ki.</hi> 12. 24. It was of the Lord, that is say you, God per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, or suffered it. So say I to your places, as <hi>Prov.</hi> 8. 15. Kings are of God, i. e. God permits them, suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers them, bears with them: and so Kings, at the best, are by toleration only from God.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Div.</speaker>
                        <p>Nothing lesse: for consider, besides what I said before of <hi>Prov.</hi> 8. 15.</p>
                        <p>First, That by him all things were made, i. e. the world, and government of the world, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 3. you dare not say it was by bare permission: nor can you of <hi>Prov.</hi> 8. 15. By me Kings raign?</p>
                        <p>Secondly, that the Lord shews Kings to be according to his will, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 15. 2. and his Ministers, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 4.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly, that the Hebrew word signifieth, In me Kings raign, noting them to be in him, that they come from him. Their state and persons are in his hand, <hi>Prov.</hi> 21. 1. So that God is in them, as his Deputies. They in him as their Author.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                        <p>Shew me those affirmative duties you promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Div.</speaker>
                        <p>The Scripture enjoyns such duties to be rendred to Kings by their Subjects which follow.</p>
                        <p>Subjects are to honour them, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 17. <hi>Honour the King.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>They are to fear them, <hi>Prov.</hi> 24. 1. <hi>Fear the Lord, and the King.</hi> These two are put together, with a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty annexed.</p>
                        <p>They are to defend them, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 26. 15. Why hast thou not kept thy Lord the King, <hi>v.</hi> 16. You are wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:100286:20"/> to dye, because you have not kept your Master the <hi>Lords anointed,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18. 3. Thou shalt not go—thou art worth ten thousand of us, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21, 16. 17. <hi>Abishai</hi> succoured <hi>David;</hi> the men of <hi>Israel</hi> sware, Thou shalt go no more with us to Battail, that thou quench not the light of <hi>Isra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>l,</hi> 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12. 17. If my King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, saith our Saviour, was of this world, then would my Servants fight, that I should not be delivered to the <hi>Jews, Joh.</hi> 18. 36.</p>
                        <p>They are to yield subjection, <hi>Ro.</hi> 13. 1. since such were the Ministers of God at that time, when <hi>Nero</hi> was Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, <hi>v.</hi> 4. <hi>Titus</hi> 3. 1. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 13. They are to sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the King as Supreme, to other Governors as to them who are sent of God, <hi>v.</hi> 14. Observe in this place, The King is called Supreme: and <hi>Samuel</hi> calleth <hi>Saul,</hi> the Head, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. 17.</p>
                        <p>They are to give Tribute to <hi>Caesar, Matth.</hi> 22. 21. <hi>Romans</hi> 13. 6. Which Christ paid, <hi>Matthew</hi> 17. 27.</p>
                        <p>They are to pray for them, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 2. Thus did the people for <hi>Saul, God save the King,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10. 24. <hi>God save King Solomon,</hi> 1 King. 1. 39. For King <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoash, God save the King,</hi> 2 King 11. 12. <hi>O King live for ever,</hi> Dan. 6. 21. Give the King thy judgments, O God, and thy righteousnesse to the Kings Son, <hi>Psal.</hi> 72. 1. Pray for the Life of the King, and of his Sons, <hi>Ezra</hi> 6. 10. <hi>Neh.</hi> 2. 3. And in <hi>Tertullians</hi> dayes the Christians prayed for their Heathen Emperours, <hi>That God would give them long life, secure Government, a safe house, valiant Souldiers, faithful Senatours, good people, and quiet Kingdomes.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>They are to obey them keeping the Kings Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, and that in regard of the oath of God, <hi>Eccl.</hi>
                           <pb n="21" facs="tcp:100286:20"/> 8. 2. To do the command of the King, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 30. 12. Whosoever will not do the law of God, and the King, let judgment be speedily executed, <hi>Ezra.</hi> 7. 26. <hi>Ierem.</hi> 27. 8.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
                        <p>But we are to obey God rather then Man.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Div.</speaker>
                        <p>Obedience is to be given only to things lawful, yet if Kings command things unlawful, we are not to resist their authority, but submit, and therein is true obedience.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
                        <p>We being all men, would not a parity, or neer to a parity do better?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Div.</speaker>
                        <p>He who affects parity, let him begin it in his own house; and as he likes it in the model, let him at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt it in the fabrick. And now Sir, I hope you are satisfied from Scripture, that Kings are of God, and that no sort of men can shew more, and better evidence, for their being of God then Kings.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
                        <p>I am very well satisfied concerning such Kings, namely of <hi>Israel:</hi> but what is all this to us, and to our Kings? Do you find in the Word, our Kings na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Div.</speaker>
                        <p>Good Sir, take heed what you say, and consider I beseech you,</p>
                        <p>That the Scriptures concern us now asmuch as the Church formerly.</p>
                        <p>That generals and universals in the same, imply par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars of that kind.</p>
                        <p>That you are not named in Scripture; yet your wives, childrens, servants, and neighbours duties to you are commanded in those general precepts. Wives reverence your husbands. Honour thy Father, Servants obey your Masters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The relative duties in such relations are enjoined now, so likewise of Kings and Subjects.</p>
                        <pb n="22" facs="tcp:100286:21"/>
                        <p> That as the duties are not enjoyned only to good hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, fathers, masters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So not only to good Kings: But to Fathers, Masters, Kings. For I pray, what was <hi>Saul, Nero,</hi> &amp;c?</p>
                        <p>And concerning our present King, I know him not, I know the want of him, and the good I lose by that want. And should I speak what I think, you would perhaps say, I did flatter: Give me leave therefore to tell you, what an Assembly-man, and an Army-man of your own sect have written of him. Mr. <hi>Wilkinson</hi> of <hi>Wadesden</hi> in <hi>Buckinghamshire,</hi> an Assembly Divine, some years since dead, in a Book of his called a Debt-book, saith (p. 22.) <hi>In Monarchies (the perfection of earthly Governments and types of the heavenly) the King is the supreme Governour; not only over all Persons, but in all Causes Ecclesiastical, and Civil:</hi> and saith, <hi>King</hi> Charles <hi>for his life hitherto unspotted of the world, so free in youth from the lust of the flesh, so far from intemperance in the fulness of plenty, so prevalent over pride in such a a fortune, so unstained by Popery in the School of</hi> Spain, <hi>so attentive and judicious of hearing Gods word, so full of all goodnesse when it was not in request,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <hi>George Withers,</hi> who hath been an Officer (as I have heard) in your Army faith of King <hi>CHARLES</hi> in his <hi>Britains Remembrance.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <q>
                           <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                              <body>
                                 <div type="poem">
                                    <lg>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>—No Kingdome hath a Prince</hi>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>Whose infant years gave better evidence▪</hi>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>That with an earthly Crown he should inherit</hi>
                                          <note place="margin">pag. 25.</note>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>A plenteous portion of the Sacred Sspirit.</hi>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>None liveth now on whom the general eye</hi>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>Did so much gaze, and so few fau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                                <desc>•</desc>
                                             </gap>ts espy:</hi>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>Few private men were in their youth so free</hi>
                                       </l>
                                       <pb n="23" facs="tcp:100286:21"/>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>From all those vanities which frequent be &amp;c.</hi>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>again</l>
                                    </lg>
                                    <lg>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>Or who of all thy Viceroys didst thou see,</hi>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>Appear more worthily devout than he, &amp;c.</hi>
                                          <note place="margin">pag. 26.</note>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>again</l>
                                    </lg>
                                    <lg>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>What Monarchy in appearance better preacheth</hi>
                                          <note place="margin">pag. 26.</note>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>By good Examples, what thy precepts teacheth?</hi>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>Or which of all his Reverend Prelacy</hi>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>In shews of true Religious constancy,</hi>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>Outgoes or equals him, &amp;c?</hi>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>again</l>
                                    </lg>
                                    <lg>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>I would not speak what might offend the Throne</hi>
                                          <note place="margin">pag. 196.</note>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>Of justice, or the King that sits thereon;</hi>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>From all vexation let him be as free</hi>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>As he is innocent, &amp;c.</hi>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>again,</l>
                                    </lg>
                                    <lg>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>—To have no power or aim,</hi>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>To touch the Lords annointed I disclaim;</hi>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>I have no warrant neither know I ought,</hi>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>To reprehend him of, although I mought.</hi>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>And they of my uprightness judge amiss,</hi>
                                          <note place="margin">pag. 226.</note>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>Who think I flatter in affirming this, &amp;c.</hi>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>again</l>
                                    </lg>
                                    <lg>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>—But neither yet,</hi>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>In him beheld I what did unbefit</hi>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>His person, or his place, much have I seen,</hi>
                                          <note place="margin">pag. 226.</note>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>That rather hath an Honor to him been,</hi>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>And whatsoever shall muttered be of some</hi>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>There raigns not any King in Christendome,</hi>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>Of whom there was divulg'd a better fame,</hi>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>Or whom a Royal Throne so well became,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
                                    </lg>
                                 </div>
                              </body>
                           </floatingText>
                        </q>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, I am fully satisfied, yea so that I with many other are ready (as <hi>Amasai</hi> to <hi>David)</hi> to return unto
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:100286:22"/> our King, and say. <hi>Thine are we, O King, and on thy</hi>
                           <note place="margin">1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12. 18.</note>
                           <hi>side, peace, peace, be unto thee,</hi> and peace be to thine hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, for thy God helpeth thee; that so he may again re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive us.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Div.</speaker>
                        <p>Do, and doubt not of an answer like <hi>Davids. If you be come peaceably unto me to help me, mine heart</hi>
                           <note place="margin">1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12. 17.</note>
                           <hi>shall be knit unto you. But if you be come to betray me to mine enemies, seeing there is no wrong in my hands, the Lord God of our Fathers look thereon, and rebuke it.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <closer>VIVAT REX, Floreat Regnum, Bene valeat Parliamentum.</closer>
                     <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:100286:22"/>
                  <p> AN ESSAY FOR Orderly Hearing <hi>DIALOGUE-WISE.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>IN WHICH
<list>
                        <item>The supposed Speakers are
<list>
                              <item>ADOLUS <hi>a sincere Christian.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>PHLUAROS <hi>a Trifler.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>PLANAETES <hi>a Wanderer.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>By <hi>JOSEPH BENTHAM,</hi> Once again <hi>Rector</hi> of the Church of <hi>Broughton</hi> in <hi>Northamptonshire.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>E. C.</hi> for <hi>William Tompson</hi> Bookseller at <hi>Harborough</hi> in <hi>Leicestershire.</hi> 1661.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:100286:23"/>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:100286:23"/>
                  <head>To the Reader.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Christian Reader,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>AT the beginning of our distracting Divisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, I penned the substance of the following Discourse, for a stay to some private Friends; fearing the sad effects we have since seen, arising from peoples needless, and contemptuous refusing to hear honest, godly, and painful Preachers of Gods Word, whom the Lord hath placed with, and over them. For too many, first leave and loath their own, then others, then all. This short Dialogue may satisfie some. If so, it is not lost labour: if not, yet I have satisfied my self, who am, and rest</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Thy true, and Christian Friend, <hi>Joseph Bentham.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:100286:24"/>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="essay">
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:100286:24"/>
                  <head>AN ESSAY FOR Orderly Hearing <hi>DIALOGƲE-WISE.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IN WHICH
<list>
                        <item>The supposed Speakers are
<list>
                              <item>ADOLUS <hi>a sincere Christian.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>PHLUAROS <hi>a Trifler.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>PLANAETES <hi>a Wanderer.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adol.</speaker>
                     <p>WHither away so fast, to day, Neighbour <hi>Phluaros?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phl.</speaker>
                     <p>To the <hi>Means,</hi> at such a place.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adol.</speaker>
                     <p>Doth not the Minister in your Town Mr. <hi>Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lokagathos</hi> Preach constantly? or, in case he should fail, doth not Mr. <hi>Pistos</hi> of the next Town to you Preach?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phl.</speaker>
                     <p>Truly, they do both Preach constantly every
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:100286:25"/> Lords day, and also Catechise the Youth of their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishes in the Principles of Religion: and usually Preach up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n dayes called Holy-dayes, at home or abroad.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adol.</speaker>
                     <p>Then you are perswaded that Mr. <hi>Kalokaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thos</hi> will Preach this Lords day at your Town?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phl.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes verily, twice; and Catechise also.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adol.</speaker>
                     <p>How dare you then, having no need, the means at home, where your Family is, travail so many miles upon this day, without cause?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phl.</speaker>
                     <p>How dare you, Goodman <hi>Adolus,</hi> move such a Question? Shall not a Christian stand fast in his Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Liberty? Shall a Christian, which is so free, be tyed to this, or that, or any man, and his Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adol.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh Neighbour! you know not your mercies you enjoy. <hi>Jesurun waxed fat and kicked,</hi> Deut. 32. 15. Had I such a Pastor as either of those, you have now balked, I should esteem it a more then ordinary favour. Our Mr. <hi>Orthodox</hi> is not like to them; yet whensoever he Preacheth, I dare not forsake him. I do often resort to him, I stir him up in a fair and friendly way, and desire him not to be offended with me, for going to some Neighbour (when himself doth not Preach) where I may hear the Word read, and a Sermon also. By this means I have his love, gain good from him in private and publick; with his good liking, I hear the Word from others. And thus doing, I stand as fast in my Christian Liberty as you do, or can.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phl.</speaker>
                     <p>If your Mr. <hi>Orthodox</hi> be the man I have heard him reported to be, were I his Parishioner, I would nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hear him, nor once come into his Company; for your Neighbour <hi>Planates</hi> saith, He is a silly Preacher;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:100286:25"/> and common-fame shews him to be a Persecutor; for by his means, your Neighbour <hi>Planaetes</hi> is ever and anon in the Court.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adol.</speaker>
                     <p>Friend <hi>Phluaeros,</hi> do not credit over confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon trust. Christ was belyed, and who is free? For his Preaching, I confess it is but once a day; yet it is so, that it should not be contemned. Goodman <hi>Planetes</hi> might, with more credit, have spoke the truth, or been silent. The Preaching of Mr. <hi>Orthodox</hi> being good, honest, and inferior to few. And I am so well acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with him, that I dare confidently affirm, that who so reports him a Persecutor, slandereth him: True it is, he doth disl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ke Goodman <hi>Planaetes</hi> doings, running a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout causelessely to his discouragement; his rash, and uncharitable censoriousness; and other offensive matters, for which he sometime; rebukes him. But I know that although Goodman <hi>Planaetes</hi> is often in the Court, yet it is never at the motion, or by the procurement of Mr. <hi>Orthodox.</hi> But his carriage is such, that the Churchwardens sometimes willingly, sometimes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingly, have presented him. And indeed such men as he, have done us a great deal of harm; for many honest peaceable men suffer through such mens sides, and by their means.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phl.</speaker>
                     <p>What? How now Goodman <hi>Adolus?</hi> Do you blame my Neighbour; mine intimate friend <hi>Planaetes,</hi> who is seldom from me, with whom I have so much reasoning and familiarity, that I take him to be a man inferiour to few for parts and pains?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adol.</speaker>
                     <p>It was better he had less abilities, or less pride; and that he took less pains, except in wayes more agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to Piety, and Christianity.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:100286:26"/>
                     <speaker>Phl.</speaker>
                     <p>Was he here, as I know he will be presently, you would not say of him as you do.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adol.</speaker>
                     <p>You know me, I hope, to be one who will speak my minde, to benefit others. And if he comes, you shall see what I will do.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phl.</speaker>
                     <p>Well, yonder he comes. Come, come along friend <hi>Planaetes;</hi> we are talking no good of you, I thought you to be an honester man. Your Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour <hi>Adolus</hi> gives you a report, will not please you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plan.</speaker>
                     <p>Brother <hi>Phluaros,</hi> you know that <hi>Adolus</hi> is no friend of ours. And we care as little for him. But will he backb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>te? what is it he saith of me?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adol.</speaker>
                     <p>Neighbour, I hate backbiting. I have often, and will again tell you my minde friendly and freely. And that I even now said, was forced from me to justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie Mr. <hi>Orthodox,</hi> whom you have slandered; for tell us, Did he ever present you? or cause you to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plan.</speaker>
                     <p>I know not, whether he did or not; he is very busie medling with me, yea more then I will thank him for.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adol.</speaker>
                     <p>You know not; yet by your means, it must be reported and rumored that he doth. Is this agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to Christianity? You know that you are a man so busie and censorious with your tongue; so careless of, that you let your Family run riot; yea so notoriously contentious, so fallacious and fraudulent, that for some disorder or other, you are in the Court Civil or Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiastical very often; and of you men say, He will do no right, nor take any wrong: and Mr. <hi>Orthodox</hi> must be blamed for your faults. And as for his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:100286:26"/> and admonishing you, he is more your friend, then you are your own, for which he should have love, not loathing. Besides you do very ill, in belying his preaching; for in so doing you wrong him, others, and your self.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plan.</speaker>
                     <p>Wherein do I belie his Preaching?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adel.</speaker>
                     <p>You say he is a silly Preacher.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plan.</speaker>
                     <p>So he is.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adol.</speaker>
                     <p>That's false. Although he is a seldom, he is no silly Preacher. When did you hear him?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plan.</speaker>
                     <p>Upon such a day.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adol.</speaker>
                     <p>If such, and such honest and able men, who then heard him, do not affirm, that that Sermon was honest and excellent; let me be blamed.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plan.</speaker>
                     <p>Would he alwayes Preach so, I should like him well, but I never heard him Preach so well.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adol.</speaker>
                     <p>You, and some such as you, have a strange humour. You first disgrace able and Orthodox Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers; and then if at their own Churches, or abroad, other men hearing, commend them; you have this creep-hole, Would they Preach thus alwayes, we would not leave them, we never heard them Preach thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Whereas, if you would speak truth, you might say, We never heard them Preach, but it was so well. For, name but the time, if you can, when Mr. <hi>Orthodox</hi> did not Preach so well, and appoint a time for us three, and some other judicious Christians to hear him, and if his Preaching be not well approved of, by understan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and conscientious men, let me be accounted what you please. But you are much like to Goodman <hi>Phluaros,</hi> who balked two men this day, who are men without exception. It is possible, he may hear good
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:100286:27"/> Sermons to day; but, I am confident, not better the those he might have heard at home.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phlu.</speaker>
                     <p>I neither blame Mr. <hi>Kalokagathos,</hi> nor Mr. <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stos;</hi> yet, to tell you the truth, they are but general Preachers. I like men who speak more against sin.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adol.</speaker>
                     <p>Take general Preaching so, as (with St. <hi>Paul) to declare unto you all the counsel of God,</hi> Act. 20. 27. they then are general Preachers, for they do thus. They keep them to their text, soundly dividing the Word, with profitable application to the good of the hearers. And this, it seems, you like not, but such who speak more against sin. I know your meaning: A preacher must read his Text, and presently inveigh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst all sorts of sins. This is the Preaching which you like. Did ever the Prophets, Apostles, or Christ preach thus? Do they not sometimes disswade from some, sometimes from other sins? Do they not some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times perswade to some, sometimes to other Graces, and Duties? And must good, and godly Preachers be accounted general; and so, as not to be heard, because they follow such patterns? Well Neighbour <hi>Phluaros,</hi> it seems, that Mr. <hi>Kalokagathos</hi> your Preacher, doth Preach upon Holy dayes. Let us three, the next Thurs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day (being Holy-day) hear him; and I believe we shall hear a Sermon, not to be faulted with this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptuous brand of General Preaching.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phl.</speaker>
                     <p>Do you think Ile hear him Preach upon an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-day? I tell you, No.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adol.</speaker>
                     <p>Time was, friend, you would have heard him, or any other good Minister Preach upon an Holy-day; at home, or elsewhere. What is the matter now? Is the Word the worse for the day? Admit it is not a Sermon
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:100286:27"/>
                        <hi>in season,</hi> yet if <hi>out of season,</hi> he may preach (2 Tim. 4. 2.) and we hear.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phl.</speaker>
                     <p>I will not.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plan.</speaker>
                     <p>Neither will I.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adol.</speaker>
                     <p>This is the Lords▪day, and now you will not. Thursday is Holy-day, and then you will not. A Preacher shall have little comfort or encouragement to take pains with such a people. I am sorry Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, you are so self-will'd in a way so sinful.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phl.</speaker>
                     <p>Sinful?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plan.</speaker>
                     <p>Will you say, we sin in thus doing?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adol.</speaker>
                     <p>I do so. And for the manifestation of the same, I will state two Questions; and in answer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them, shew how you two doe sinne both wayes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phl.</speaker>
                     <p>Let us hear your goodly questions.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adol.</speaker>
                     <p n="1">1. Whether people having a Preaching Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister, approved of, by godly Divines and People, for life and Doctrine; may out of their partial pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicate opinion, absent themselves from his Sermons on Holy-dayes, or other week-dayes, they having no urgent occasions necessitating that their absence, only their unworthy conceit of the Minister?</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Whether they may leave their own Church and Pastor, he Preaching, and travel ordinarily certain miles to hear others, at the same time they know their own doth without doubt Preach?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phl.</speaker>
                     <p>What is your Answer to the first of your Questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons so stated?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adol.</speaker>
                     <p>I think that their absenting of themselves is unlawful.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:100286:28"/>
                     <speaker>Phl.</speaker>
                     <p>It matters not what you think: prove it unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful if you can.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adol.</speaker>
                     <p>I prove it sinful or unlawful, from three grounds; namely, <hi>Scripture, Scandal Breach of whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some Laws.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="1">1. From <hi>Scripture.</hi> Mat. 22. 2. Luke 14. 16. <hi>The Dinner,</hi> is expounded by some, <hi>the preaching of the Word:</hi> where God feeds his guests with his delicates. They who absented themselves for <hi>Farms, Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dise,</hi> and <hi>Wiving,</hi> are accounted <hi>unworthy to taste,</hi> &amp;c. Luke 14. 24. Further, if <hi>Martha</hi> for doing that which Humanity, Reason and Religion, enjoyned her (name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for making provision for such a Preacher as Christ, because at that time when Christ was Preaching) was reproved: then certainly people do offend, who for sleight, or no occasions, absent themselves from hearing the Word Preached at their doors. This is also that <hi>Kingdom,</hi> that <hi>Treasure,</hi> that <hi>Pearl,</hi> which the wise Merchant doth so prize as to <hi>sell all to buy it,</hi> Mat. 13. 44, 45. And therefore should much more take, when he may enjoy it by parting with an hours work for it. And, Psal. 122. 1. <hi>I was glad;</hi> and 1 Pet. 2. 2. do shew, <hi>That gracious men, new-born Christians, do ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly desire, and joyfully take, all fitting occasions for hearing.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. From <hi>Scandal.</hi> The absence of people professing Religion, is a main occasion of others absence, and so may be of their Damnation. We are too much led by example. Ignorant and natural men, are ready to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son thus, Was there such necessity, utility, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in hearing of the Word, as Preachers tell us, surely people who have been long hearers, would not
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:100286:28"/> so ordinarily, and carelesly absent themselves. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly therefore Preachers misinform us in this, and why not in other things? therefore we will not believe them. Such men then, in so doing, may occasion other men; Damnation, and be guilty of the same. Worthy was the example of a Nobleman, who being deaf, <note place="margin">An old E. of K.</note> yet for an example to draw others, would not be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. From <hi>the Law.</hi> Against which, such men sin. Certainly, Laws tending to Piety, are to be obeyed. The Book of Common-prayer <note n="*" place="margin">Was when this was pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</note> is established by Law; in it, Holy-dayes; on them, Ministers are commanded to Pray, read Scripture, Catechise, and permitted to Preach; and People are enjoyned to be present, and to hear. Therefore people causelessely absenting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves (as you two out of self-will only) do unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phl.</speaker>
                     <p>How do you prove your second?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adol.</speaker>
                     <p>I would not be misunderstood. I understand this of ordinary absenting themselves: not of absenting upon some extraordinary occasions.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phl.</speaker>
                     <p>Well, well, prove that we sin (as to day) in so doing. Which you say you can.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adol.</speaker>
                     <p>I will; and shew, that in thus doing, you sin against
<list>
                           <item>1. God.</item>
                           <item>2. The Church of God.</item>
                           <item>3. Your own Pastor.</item>
                           <item>4. The Minister whom you go to hear.</item>
                           <item>5. The Day.</item>
                           <item>6. Your common Neighbour.</item>
                           <item>7. Your Christian Brother.</item>
                           <pb n="38" facs="tcp:100286:29"/>
                           <item> 8. Such who dwell where means are wanting.</item>
                           <item>9. Your selves.</item>
                           <item>10. Your Families.</item>
                           <item>11. The rules of Christianity.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plan.</speaker>
                     <p>Sayes he so, Brother <hi>Pluaros?</hi> We have need to look what we do; if he can prove what he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phl.</speaker>
                     <p>Tush brother, he doth but vapor; these are but bubbles of winde, which will come to nothing.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plan.</speaker>
                     <p>How ever, let us hear what he can say.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phl.</speaker>
                     <p>Content. <hi>Adolus,</hi> prove that we sin against God in thus doing.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adol.</speaker>
                     <p>By thus doing, you sin against God three wayes. For</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Whereas God by weak means, doth often his grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test works; you tie the Lord to such means, to such men and Ministers to save your souls.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. You sin against God, despising such means and mercies he gives you. Every man should think his own wife best for him. Every man should prize Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies bestowed upon himself. But you contemn his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours. <hi>Israels</hi> despising <hi>Manna,</hi> and the pleasant Land was a sin displeasing God.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. You also sin, in not being thankful to him for his benefits. Such who have a mercy and know it not, or disdain it, or are not contented with it, will never be thankful for that mercy.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phl.</speaker>
                     <p>How do we sin against the Church?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adol.</speaker>
                     <p>You sin against the Church, the Common-wealth, and Laws of both.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Which enjoyn people there to hear; where they enjoyn the Minister of the Word to officiate. For
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:100286:29"/> should the Law leave people at their own discretion, to do as seemed them good, it would open a gap to many disorders, some affecting one Minister, some another, some the Glover, or Smith before all. Like some diseased stomachs, which desire things hurtful, and to be abhorred, before the most nourishing dainties.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. And it would be to little or no purpose for the Church, and Common-wealth to enjoyn Ministers to read, Preach, &amp;c. if people also were not enjoyned to (and obediently did) hear, and joyn with them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phl.</speaker>
                     <p>How do we sin against our own Ministers?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adol.</speaker>
                     <p>Four manner of wayes.
<list>
                           <item n="1">1. Contemning them, whom you are to
<list>
                                 <item>1. Honour, 1 Tim. 5. 17.</item>
                                 <item>2. Obey, Heb. 13. 17.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item n="2">2. Slandering of them, and that two wayes.
<list>
                                 <item n="1">1. In your Words; for meeting with your Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, you fall into communication. And they asking you, Why are you here? What doth you Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister to day?</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Then of necessity you must condemn,</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Your selves, saying, We have itching ears, desirous of Novelties; we grow wanton through abundance of Preaching. But you love your selves too much to say thus.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Or your Ministers, after this or the like sort They are good honest men, they do what they can, they give good counsel; But we had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther go ten miles to hear a Sermon from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, then over the threshold to hea them.</p>
                     <p n="2">
                        <pb n="40" facs="tcp:100286:30"/> 2. In your actions; which (should you be silent) do abundantly slander them.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Discouraging, disheartning, and so disabling them from the work of their functions. The work of the minde consisting in Meditation, is much disabled by discouragements and vexations. Many men or mean parts of art and nature, meeting with an encouraging people, have improved them: whereas many of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent parts have suffered an eclipse by peoples way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardness.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. Depriving them of much joy and fruit, they might otherwise have gained in their Ministery. And of much thankfulness they might have given to God, for an encouraging profiting people.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phlu.</speaker>
                     <p>You told us, that we sinned against the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters we go to hear, in thus leaving our own. How I pray?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adol.</speaker>
                     <p>Four manner of wayes.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. In being an occasion of pride in them. For if St. <hi>Paul</hi> was so subject to this, that God sent the buffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Satan to prevent it, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 7. why should we think that Ministers are now free from it. Even he to whom you are now going, knowing that Mr. <hi>Kalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>hos,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Pistos</hi> are very able men; and well approved of for life and doctrine; and seeing some of their people come to hear him, he hath a great temptation and provocation to be high-minded.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. In occasioning enmity and emulation between him and them; so between these who are fellow La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers, and do the same work.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. In occasioning some or other maliciously to exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate his gifts and parts, so much admired by you.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:100286:30"/> For men of understanding seeing you to take so much pains causelessely, are ready, as to condemn your indiscre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, so to speak to the disparagement of him, upon this occasion by you offered; which otherwise they had not done.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. In opening a gap to loose and lasie people of his Congregation, to gad whither they please. For, may not such conclude, Such and such men come from places where they have very good and able Preachers. We may therefore as well leave ours, as they theirs, and go whither we please. Therefore we will never more hear this man, although the charge of our souls is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to him; since that which is lawful to others, is lawful to us.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phlu.</speaker>
                     <p>How do we sin against the Day, being the Lords-day?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adol.</speaker>
                     <p>Two manner of wayes.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Because such dayes are dayes of Thanksgiving and Rejoycing. What joy? (yea how is a mans joy and rejoycing calmed?) by tedious travail many miles?</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Also hereby neglecting the duties of the day in private, if not publick. And occasioning others by your example to neglect the same.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phlu.</speaker>
                     <p>How do we sin against our common Neig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adol.</speaker>
                     <p>Two manner of wayes.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Making him to dislike the Ordinances, by your shewing such dislike to them; and so more unfit to be wrought upon. He concluding, Since you (who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume to know what you do) will not hear your and his Preacher; why should he regard what he saith?</p>
                     <p n="2">
                        <pb n="42" facs="tcp:100286:31"/> 2. Making him to disesteem his Pastor. He reaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from your example. So you are an occasion of his sin.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phlu.</speaker>
                     <p>How do we sin against our Christian brethren, who do not go with us?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adol.</speaker>
                     <p>Two manner of wayes.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Taking from them some part (as much as you can) of that good opinion they have to such means God hath afforded them. For, some conceiving well, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers shewing a bad conceit (and they being well estee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of) makes the others good opinion wavering and staggering.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Condemning them of ease, idleness, and sloth; preserring them before their eternal salvation. If you do well.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phlu.</speaker>
                     <p>How do we sin against those who dwell in other places where means are not?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adol.</speaker>
                     <p>Two wayes also.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Causing them to neglect the hearing of many good Sermons, which conveniently they might have heard; they being disswaded by your doings (most men being much led by examples), They are ready to say, If it was worth our labour to hear Mr. <hi>Orthodox, Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stos,</hi> &amp;c. their own Parishioners would keep at home, they Preaching; and not go abroad; yea far (as they do), to hear elsewhere. Therefore it is as good for us to stay at home, or loyter about, as to go thither, where we shall get no good.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Occasioning such to condemn good men, they not knowing for what; only from the carriage of some factious discontented people, who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> not any thing will long please.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:100286:31"/>
                     <speaker>Phul.</speaker>
                     <p>Do we sin against our Selves too?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adol.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes that you do, four manner of wayes.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Bringing your selves under a curse, when God doth not. <hi>Amos</hi> 8. 11. God threatneth it as a grievous judgement to make People <hi>wander for the Word.</hi> To be put to wander is a judgement; and to pull upon your selves a cross, when God sends none, makes you sin against your selves.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Giving just occasion of suspicion that you are Pharisees, doing what you do for vain-glory to be seen of men. When you hear at home, you do but like others, and the common sort of people, and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Christians: But your going far abroad, makes you to be eyed, talked of, and taken notice to be more forward then others.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Making your selves guilty of the bloud of many souls, which might have been saved, had not your dispa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging the means of grace hindered the same.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. Shewing you to be <hi>carnal,</hi> 1 Cor. 1. 2. &amp; 3. 3, 4. Any one of those Preachers might have served well; yet, some being for one, some for another; the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle shewes that they were <hi>faulty,</hi> that they were <hi>carnal.</hi> Your way is an old sin, with a new glosse o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phlu.</speaker>
                     <p>Do we sin also against our Families?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hdol.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes that you do, three wayes.
<list>
                           <item>1. In not going before them by good example.</item>
                           <item>2. In leaving them to their own wayes, whom you should govern and direct.</item>
                           <item>3. In depriving them of the comfort (if not use) of the Means, leaving them to look to Children, which cannot be so well awed and ordered, as by their Parents.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:100286:32"/>
                     <speaker>Phlu.</speaker>
                     <p>And do we sin, against the rules of Christia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adol.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes: these four, to name no more, Christia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity requires.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. <hi>All things to be don decently and in order,</hi> 1 Cor. 14. 40. Your carriage opens a door to confusion and disorder.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. <hi>All things to be done in Charity,</hi> 1 Cor. 16. 14. What greater sin against Charity, then to occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion division between Pastor and People; People and People?</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Christianity enjoynes people <hi>to think Paul and Apolles both, to be only Ministers,</hi> (and no more) by whom men believe, to be but <hi>planters</hi> and <hi>waterers,</hi> and to think that <hi>the increase is only of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 3. 5, 6, 7, 8. Who gives often the greatest blessings to the weakest means, that himself may have the greater glory.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. And commands us▪ <hi>Not to have the faith of Christ with respect of persons,</hi> Jam. 2. 1.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plan.</speaker>
                     <p>How now, Neighbour? I think he hath non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plussed you. I am sure he hath pusled me so, that I shall think of another course, and turn over a new leaf.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phlu.</speaker>
                     <p>Silly man, wilt thou be moved from thy opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with words? I tell thee, it is not Words, Reasons, Scriptures, any thing, shall stir me from the way where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I resolve to walk.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plan.</speaker>
                     <p>You say true, I am silly a and the more simple I was in being so much led by you into wayes so sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and offensive. But although I have <hi>walked in the council of the ungodly, and stood in the way of sinners;</hi>
                        <pb n="45" facs="tcp:100286:32"/> yet I hope I shall not <hi>sit in the seat of the scornful.</hi> For since your resolution is, as you say, farewel once my familiar <hi>Phluaros;</hi> and Ile go along with you now friend <hi>Adolus,</hi> whom I see to be plain, honest, and to seek my good.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phlu.</speaker>
                     <p>He seek thy good, who goeth about to quench thy zeal!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adol.</speaker>
                     <p>I cool no mans zeal; but stir up all to be zealous for God, and in the wayes of godliness. I love a good fire, provided it be in the Chimney, not in the house-top. I like and cherish a good metled horse, but am careful to have him well man'd and mannaged. And I much respect and encourage a Christian furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed <hi>with zeal according to knowledg,</hi> and accompanied <hi>with charity and discretion.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phlu.</speaker>
                     <p>Ile have no more to do with you <hi>Planaetes,</hi> if you will joyn with <hi>Adolus;</hi> for I am sure that he and I shall never well agree together.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plan.</speaker>
                     <p>Nor I with you any more, of whom I have learned much evill and no good. For, friend <hi>Adolus,</hi> it is he who drew me into these exorbitant wayes, To forsake our Preacher, to go sometimes to this, some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to that man; and after to speak evill of, and scorn them all; to censure and condemn the most. For presently after the Sermon, he would be finding fault with the Sermon; or, with the Government; or, with some body or other. As if Religion consisted in blaming others, amending none, much lesse our selves. And hence it is, that he and I have been so scandalous to the Gospel. But I hope, with Gods help, and your good furtherance, to be a new man.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adol.</speaker>
                     <p>If you will be ruled by me, Neighbour <hi>Planaetes,</hi>
                        <pb n="46" facs="tcp:100286:33"/> then love your Minister, as one sent of God, to do you good; for if you dislike him, you will never profit by his Preaching.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plan.</speaker>
                     <p>But you know he Preacheth but once a day.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adol.</speaker>
                     <p>For my part I love, and like best such Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters who Preach twice. And every Lords day I hear two Sermons, one at home, the other abroad. Do not therefore think that I justifie any mans negligence. Yet, Neighbour <hi>Planaetes,</hi> take notice of these two things.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. That you never condemn any man without suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient warrant. And what warrant have you to condemn Mr. <hi>Orthodox</hi> for but once Preaching? For in what place of Scripture is a Minister commanded to Preach twice every Lords day?</p>
                     <p n="2">2. That our Mr. <hi>Orthodox</hi> his one Sermon, shewes him to be more diligent, then the twice Preaching of some men do them. His once is learned, yet plain, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest, conscientious, and edifying. Whereas some who presume to Preach twice, speak very much, yet very little. I know that Mr. <hi>Kalokagathos,</hi> Mr. <hi>Pistos,</hi> and many more godly Ministers about us, preach twice day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, soundly and substantially, blessed be God for it. But there are too many pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>suming to do so without either abilities, or pains taking, who speak much to little pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose. Was it not better that these would imitate Mr. <hi>Orthodox,</hi> and so labor more in the Word and Doctrine, rather then to vent such crude and indigested matter as some do? One of Mr. <hi>Orthodox</hi> his contemned Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, hath more sound edifying Divinity in it, than twenty of such.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plan.</speaker>
                     <p>Well then, I will hear him when he Preacheth; and when he doth not Preach, I will go with you to some Neighbouring Church.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:100286:33"/>
                     <speaker>Adol.</speaker>
                     <p>But, Neighbour <hi>Planaetes,</hi> if you will joyn in friendship with <hi>Adolus</hi> I tell you plainly, <hi>You</hi> must amend your life, else I will have nothing to do with you. <hi>You</hi> must be a doer as well as an hearer of Gods Word. <hi>You</hi> must shew your faith by its fruits. Live harmelesly and inoffensively at home and abroad. Order and educate your family better, teaching them to know and serve <hi>God. You</hi> must follow your calling religiously diligently, faithfully, charitably, and lawfully. <hi>You</hi> must leave your contentious wranglings, and rash censurings, and live at peace. <hi>You</hi> must live alwayes as in Gods presence; and evidence that you have <hi>Gods Spirit by the fruits thereof in your life,</hi> as <hi>love, joy, peace, long suffering, gentleness, goodness, faith, meekness, and temperance,</hi> Gal. 5. 22, 23. Shewing that you have <hi>that wisedom which is from above</hi> by being <hi>pure, peaceable, gentle, easie to be intreated, full of mercy, and good fruits, without partiality, without hypocrisie,</hi> Jam. 3. 17.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plan.</speaker>
                     <p>God assisting, I will be your friend, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low you in all things.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adol.</speaker>
                     <p>I shall gadly do you or any man good; that so I may bring glory to God.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:100286:34"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:100286:34"/>
                  <p> A DEFENCE OF Psalm-Singing <hi>DIALOGƲE-WISE.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>IN WHICH
<list>
                        <item>The supposed Speakers are
<list>
                              <item>HODAEGOS <hi>a Guide.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>AUTHADAES <hi>a proud Caviller.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>PLANAES <hi>one misled, yet conscientious.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>By <hi>JOSEPH BENTHAM,</hi> Once again <hi>Rector</hi> of the Church of <hi>Broughton</hi> in <hi>Northamptonshire.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>E. C.</hi> for <hi>William Tompson</hi> Bookseller at <hi>Harborough</hi> in <hi>Leicestershire.</hi> 1661.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:100286:35"/>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:100286:35"/>
                  <head>To the Reader.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Christian Reader,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>IN these distracted times, people too much run upon Negatives; No Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tism, No Lords Supper, No Ministery, No Set Forms of Prayer, No observing of dayes, No Churches, No Repentance, No sorrow for sin, No singing of Psalms, with too many other such like; which all are against God, namely, his Messengers, his Ordinances, his Houses, and his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. And whereas Religion consists not in <hi>Nots</hi> and <hi>Noes,</hi> Luke 18. 11. For a man may be no Drunkard, no Adulterer, no Ʋsurer; He may not Steal, nor Kill, not Swear; yet be far from Sanctification and Salvation: yet many now think it sufficient, Not to hear Serm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ns from
<pb facs="tcp:100286:36"/> Ordained Ministers, Not to have their children Baptized, Not to come to the Lords Table, Not to sing Psalms, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> A duty as the rest, not only lawful, and lau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>able; but also very necessary, pious, and profitable: much tending to Instructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Edification; to Comfort and Conso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of good men. Of late years, having had reasoning with some Cavilling Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temners of this so solacing and soul-ravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing a Duty, although to little purpose in regard of them; yet by that discourse with them, I saw their Grounds (such as they are; the weakness whereof, as of some o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, I here discover, to settle others in the I ruth, that they may not be turned unto the vain and ungodly errours of such people.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Thus I am, and rest, thy true Christian Friend, <hi>Joseph Bentham,</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="dialogue">
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:100286:36"/>
                  <head>A DEFENCE OF Psalm-singing <hi>DIALOGƲE-WISE.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IN WHICH</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>The supposed Speakers are
<list>
                           <item>HODAEGOS <hi>a Guide.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>AUTHADAES <hi>a proud Caviller.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>PLANAES <hi>one misled, yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scientious.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>WEll met Neighbours, <hi>Authadaes</hi> and <hi>Planaes;</hi> you two continue still your old and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate acquaintance.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Auth.</speaker>
                     <p>Why should we not, Mr. <hi>Hodaegos?</hi> we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the same minde and Church. There being few of us, we have the more need to company toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and communicate to the edifying of one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:100286:37"/>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>I condemn not, but commend you, for your loving society; and for endeavouring to edifie each other; provided you do, as you say; stirring up one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to Repentance, newness of life, Sanctification. And that you do not harden each other in wayes not war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable by the Word, which are contrary to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stianity.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Auth.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh Sir: you legal Teachers have too long enslaved us to duties, as Praying, Hearing, Repenting, and I know not what; but, now we know our Liberty, we will take it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>Friend, do not say, that we enslave you, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swading you to do what the Scripture enjoyns; for we, perswading you to Scripture-duties, perswade you but to serve God; which I am sure is no slavery, but perfect freedom.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Auth.</speaker>
                     <p>You say, every thing you are pleased to presse on us, is a Scripture-duty; as the last time we met, you would have me believe, that <hi>Singing of Psalms</hi> was a <hi>Scripture-duty;</hi> but I am so far from thinking it to be so, that I cannot endure the same, although I was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly much delighted with it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>Here is a Bible, Can you read?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Auth.</speaker>
                     <p>You need not mock Sir, you know I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not read one word, nor do I know one letter of a book.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>And hence it is, that you are so conceited, so censorious, and so unchristian, as to abuse those who wish you well, as you did me after our last confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, reporting me to say, what I did not; and other things otherwise then I did.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:100286:37"/>
                     <speaker>Auth.</speaker>
                     <p>Did I so? If I did, the weakness of my memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry was the cause. Let us therefore, if you please, reason again of the same subject.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>Rather the abundance of your Malice, and plenty of your Pride. Did you scruple this, or any other thing, so as to desire to confer with me to be satisfied; you (as any other, although never so mean) should finde me as willing as you could wish? But since, I know, it is only out of a cavilling disposition, and that you may go tatling about, that you have non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plus'd Mr. <hi>Hodaegos,</hi> so that he had nothing to say; I tell you true, I will not so far honour any such self-conceited Caviller, as to confer with him. But as for you, Neighbour <hi>Planaes,</hi> you having more knowledge, and being a man, as I conceive, who make conscience of your wayes, if you will propound any scruples which this Caviller, or any other, have troubled you withall, concerning <hi>Singing of Psalms,</hi> I am ready to satisfie you, and shall think my time and pains very well spent in so doing.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plan.</speaker>
                     <p>Truly, Mr. <hi>Hodaegos,</hi> I was formerly delighted with <hi>Singing of Psalms,</hi> and did dayly in my house sing with my Family; but my Neighbour <hi>Authades,</hi> and others, have drawn me much to dislike, and wholly to neglect, the same.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>And why do you dislike and neglect <hi>singing of Psalms,</hi> which you formerly used?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Auth.</speaker>
                     <p>Why should he not?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>I speak not to you: Civility, had you any good manners, would teach you, to let your Neighbour an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer for himself.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:100286:38"/>
                     <speaker>Plan.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, I will answer as <hi>Authadaes</hi> hath done. Why should I not?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>Truly, Friend, your answer and his, shew the sad condition of those who dote upon such Teachers and Leaders. I would know the grounds of your for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saking the true way, and you answer, Why should you not? To which I will answer, Because you ought not. And you ought not, because it is a Scripture-du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Auth.</speaker>
                     <p>Hark, Neighbour, hark. He is up again with his duties. Since you can read the Scriptures, presse him to shew it from Scripture, and see that he quotes right. Could I but read, I'de handle him soundly, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mittens, I warrant you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plan.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, What warrant from Scripture have you for Singing of Psalms?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>Abundance from Scripture, which for method and memory sake, I will draw into four heads, and shew that this duty is grounded on Scripture.</p>
                     <p>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. From precepts of the holy Ghost to sing.</item>
                           <item>2. From the practice of holy men singing.</item>
                           <item>3. From the benefits arising from the duty of singing.</item>
                           <item>4. From Scripture-directions how to sing.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plan.</speaker>
                     <p>What are your Scriptures which command this duty (as you call it) of singing of Psalms.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>Psal. 30. 4. <hi>Sing unto the Lord, O ye Saints of his.</hi> Psal. 33. 2, 3. <hi>Sing unto him with the Psal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>y. Sing unto him a new song.</hi> Psal. 47. 6. <hi>Sing pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> to God, sing praises: sing praises to our King.</hi> Psal. 68. 4. <hi>Sing unto God, sing praises to his name.</hi> ver. 32. <hi>Sing unto God, ye Kingdoms of the earth. O sing praises unto</hi>
                        <pb n="57" facs="tcp:100286:38"/>
                        <hi>the Lord.</hi> Psal. 95. 1. <hi>O come let us sing unto the Lord.</hi> Isa. 42. 10. <hi>Sing unto the Lord a new Song.</hi> Jer. 20. 13. <hi>Sing unto the Lord.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Auth.</speaker>
                     <p>Neighbour, How can you have so much pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience? Are not all his places named, in the old Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p n="1">1. A man had need to have no small measure of Patience, who deals with such men as you are; who cannot distinguish between that part of the old Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which concerns the <hi>Jewish cerremonies</hi> their <hi>particular politie,</hi> and that part which contains the <hi>perpetual rule of Gods will,</hi> and <hi>necessary truths for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians to knew.</hi> Hence it is, that some of you deny one, some another, some a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l the Commandements of God.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. You say, The places alledged are in the Old Testament. They are so, but no whit the lesse Authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical; for the same God who spake in the one, speaks in the other. Both are Gods Word. Christ and his Apostles use the Authority of the Old Testament. Our Saviour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22. 32. alledgeth a place from <hi>Exod.</hi> 3. 6. In <hi>Mat.</hi> 11 5. he alledgeth Scripture from <hi>Isa.</hi> 35. 6. &amp; 61. 1. In <hi>Luke</hi> 4. 17, 18. He preacheth upon <hi>Isa,</hi> 61. 1. And <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 39. He commands to <hi>search the Scriptures,</hi> which then were only the Old Testament. St. <hi>Peter</hi> alleadgeth the Prophets to <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius, Act.</hi> 10. 43. And St. <hi>Paul</hi> affirmes <hi>all Scripture to be of God, and profitable,</hi> 2 Tim. 3. 16.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. The writings of the Prophets, differ not from the writings of the Apostles in regard of the Doctrine. For the same Doctrine of Faith, and Doctrine of M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners is taught in them: But in regard of the time. So
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:100286:39"/> that the Prophets prophesie of Christ to come: the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles shew he is come. The Old Testament is the foundation of the New: The New is the accompl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>sh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Old. The Prophets doctrine is as the seed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time; the Apostles as the harvest. What is obscurely shadowed in the Prophets, is clearly unfolded in the Apostles. So that by adding the New Testament, the Word of God is not more perfect; but, more plain: for the Old was p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rfect, and sufficient in regard of the sense, although not in regard of the words.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. And whereas you tell him. The places are in the Old Testament; I moreover tell him, That had not you interrupted me, I had before this time shewed him Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts in the New Testament.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plan.</speaker>
                     <p>I pray, Sir, let me hear them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>Eph. 5. 19. <hi>Speaks to your selves with Psalms, and hymnes, and spiri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ual Songs; singing and making melody in your hearts to the Lord.</hi> Col. 3. 16. <hi>Teaching and admonishing one another in Ps<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>lms, Hymnes, and spiritual Songs, singing with grace in your hearts to the Lord.</hi> James 5. 13. <hi>Is any merry, let him sing Psalms?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Auth.</speaker>
                     <p>Do you not mark, Neighbour, he is up with his Songs too. What shall we have next?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>Although you take liberty to scoffe at me, yet be more careful, you scoffe not at God. I use the very words of the holy Ghost, who names Psalms, Hymns, and spiritual Songs. But it is lamentable to see what great boldness there is when Ignorance guides, and Pride rules men. And since you make your self meny with my mentioning of Songs from Scripture; know for your learning, that in Gods Word Songs are put,</p>
                     <p n="1">
                        <pb n="59" facs="tcp:100286:39"/> 1. Sometimes for the matter of the Song. <hi>I am</hi> (saith <hi>Job) their song; i. e.</hi> The matter of such mens Songs, <hi>Job</hi> 30. 8, 9. The Lord was <hi>Davids</hi> Song, <hi>Psal.</hi> 118. 14. And Gods Statutes were his Songs, <hi>Psal.</hi> 119. 54.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Sometimes for singing that which was made a song. <hi>Prov.</hi> 25. 20. <hi>Singeth songs to an heavy heart. Isa.</hi> 24. 9. <hi>Not drink wine with a song.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Know further, that Scripture makes mention of four sorts of Songs.
<list>
                           <item>1. Ungodly Songs. <hi>Job</hi> 30. 9. <hi>I am their song. Ps<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>l.</hi> 69. 12. <hi>I am the song of the drunk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>rds. Lam.</hi> 3. 14. <hi>I was their song.</hi> V. 63. <hi>I am their musick.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>2. Mystical Songs. <hi>Rev.</hi> 14. 3. <hi>They sung as it were a new song,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                           <item>3. Spiritual Songs. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5 19. So called,
<list>
                                 <item>1. Because such were sung by the motion of the Spirit, 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 14. 15, 26.</item>
                                 <item>2. And because they were sung with a spiritual mind and affections to the Lord.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>4. Divine, as that of <hi>Moses, De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>ah, Hannah,</hi> and such other.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Take notice moreover, that the Scripture men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioneth.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. New Songs. <hi>Psal.</hi> 144. 9. <hi>I will sing a new song to thee, O Lor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. Rev.</hi> 5. 9. <hi>They sung a new song.</hi> Such which were for singular and excellent use; and such which were renewed upon new and several occasions, <hi>Psal.</hi> 98. 1.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Songs of the Lord, 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 29. 27. such which were of Gods appointment for that service.</p>
                     <p n="3">
                        <pb n="60" facs="tcp:100286:40"/> 3. Songs of the Temple, <hi>i. e.</hi> sung in the Temple, at their worship there, <hi>Amos</hi> 8. 3.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. Songs of the Sabbath. <hi>Psal.</hi> 92. 1. <hi>A song for the Sabbath, i. e.</hi> appointed for the Sabbath, or, the day of holy rest, to be solemnly sung in the holy Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies upon that day. Should I tell you, that the <hi>Chalde Paraphrast</hi> saith, <hi>It was an Hymne or Song which the first man</hi> Adam <hi>said for the Sabbath;</hi> or, what some writers say: you would but scoffe, as your manner is. Only let me wish you to take notice that there are good and godly Songs mentioned in Scripture.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plan.</speaker>
                     <p>Truly Neighbour, you are too much over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seen.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Auth.</speaker>
                     <p>A good Horse may sometimes stumble. But do you hear, Neighbour; hold him to his place in the <hi>Eph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>sians.</hi> And let him clear three things if he can.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. The Apostle in that place would have us be fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with the spirit. How dares he, and his fellowes then reprove me, and such as I am, for doing things by the Spirit?</p>
                     <p n="2">2. The Apostle mentions Psalms, Hymnes, and spiritual Songs. He and his companions are only for Psalms.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. The Apostle enjoynes us to speak to our selves; to make melody in our hearts; what is this to their shouting and clamorous noise which they make, many of them together?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>But he is an ill horse who so stumbleth, as to spurn his Master. And he is no good man, who will scoffe at God in his Word. As for those three Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections: They shew the Cavillers simplicity; and the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:100286:40"/> misery of those men who follow such guides. Consider, Neighbour <hi>Planaes,</hi> that those words shew the matter, manner, and end of Musick to good men.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. His first Objection from being filled with the Spirit, is silly and slanderous.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. For we with the Apostle disswade men from the inordinate desire of Earthly things; from fulness of Wine, being drunkenness. To be filled with Wine, and to be drunk, being all one, <hi>Act.</hi> 2. 13, 15.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. We also perswade men to be filled with the Spirit; <hi>i. e.</hi> the gifts and graces of the Spirit, as <hi>love, joy, peace,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 22, 23. And with spiritual thoughts and meditations of divine joy, faith, zeal, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> well know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that <hi>if any have not the Spirit of Christ, he is none of Christs, Rom.</hi> 8. 9.</p>
                     <p>But this we also affirm, That men who live in Lying, Swearing, Rayling, Strife, Sedition, Heresies, shew that they want the Spirit, and walk after the flesh, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 20, 24. And that such men as this <hi>Authadaes</hi> are not to presume to preach to the people, because they say, They are enabled by the Spirit. For Gods way of calling men to this office is Ordinary, which they have not; or, Extraordinary, which they also want; because when God ever called men Extraordinarily, he furnished them with extraordinary gifts, to warrant their extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary calling; which guifts such men have not, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no such calling.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. His second Cavil, at the words Psalms, Hymnes, and spiritual Songs, shews his simplicity; For if we should sinfully omit singing of Hymns, and spiritual Songs, this did not at all justifie his speaking against singing of Psalms. The words are clear for our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:100286:41"/> although there is some difference amongst Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitors concerning the several words. For</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Some do understand by,
<list>
                           <item>1. <hi>Psalms,</hi> all the Psalms of <hi>David.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>2. <hi>Hymnes,</hi> the songs of <hi>Moses, Deborah;</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther such recorded in Scripture.</item>
                           <item>3. <hi>Songs,</hi> such as are composed by the faithful themselves, concerning the benefits of God.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. Some do understand by,
<list>
                           <item n="1">1. <hi>Psalms,</hi> such of the Psalms of <hi>David,</hi> by which we are taught what we should do, what we should avoid. Such which stir up to well doing, and an holy life, as <hi>Psal.</hi> 1. 37, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item n="2">2. <hi>Hymnes,</hi> such which speak of the praise of God, as of his Power, Majesty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as <hi>Psal.</hi> 107. 111, 114 <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item n="3">3. <hi>Spiritual Songs,</hi> such which are of the eternal joy, and whereby we admire the works and benefits of God, as <hi>Psal.</hi> 8. 20, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3. Some do understand by,
<list>
                           <item n="1">1. <hi>Psalms,</hi> all such which comprehend Prayers, Deprecations, Consolations.</item>
                           <item n="2">2. <hi>Hymnes,</hi> such which more pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>perly tend to the leading of men to God.</item>
                           <item n="3">3. <hi>Spiritual Songs,</hi> such which are composed more artificially then other. Affirming, that <hi>Mizmor</hi> (which hath the signification of Pruning, or cutting off super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous twigs) sign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>fieth a Song accurately and artificially written, being derived of <hi>Zamar,</hi> which signifieth to Prune: whereas <hi>Shir</hi> notes out one, not so artificially penned.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p n="4">
                        <pb n="63" facs="tcp:100286:41"/> 4. Mr. <hi>Pasor</hi> in his Lexicon saith, that
<list>
                           <item>1. A <hi>Song</hi> is a general word, and doth sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie <hi>singing,</hi> which the voice of man doth tunably sing.</item>
                           <item>2. A <hi>Psalm</hi> doth signifie the singing with Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</item>
                           <item>3. An <hi>Hymne</hi> doth signifie a <hi>Song</hi> whereby the praises of God are rehearsed.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p n="5">5. Mr. <hi>Leigh</hi> in his <hi>Critica Sacra,</hi> saith,
<list>
                           <item>1. <hi>Psalms</hi> contain Exhortations to manners, or holy life.</item>
                           <item>2. <hi>Hymnes</hi> contain praises to God, in commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of his benefits.</item>
                           <item>3. <hi>Songs</hi> contain doctrine of the chief good, of mans et<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>rnal happiness.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>The same Author in the same place saith,
<list>
                           <item>1. A <hi>Psalm</hi> is a Ditty to be played upon an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strument.</item>
                           <item>2. An <hi>Hymne</hi> is a Song to be uttered with the voice only.</item>
                           <item>3. An <hi>Ode</hi> or <hi>Song,</hi> is a Ditty fitted for either way.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p n="6">6. But if we well observe, we shall finde in the book of Psalms, some of the Psalms cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ed by the name of,
<list>
                           <item>1. <hi>A Song,</hi> as Psal. 45. <hi>of Loves,</hi> Psal. 46. <hi>upon Alamoth.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>2. <hi>A Song of degrees,</hi> as Psal. 120, 121, 122, 123, 124, 125, 126, 127, 128, 129, 130, 131, 132, 133, 134.</item>
                           <item>3. <hi>A Psalm and Song,</hi> as Psal. 30.</item>
                           <item>4. <hi>A Song and Psalm,</hi> as Psal. 48.</item>
                           <pb n="64" facs="tcp:100286:42"/>
                           <item> 5. <hi>A Psalm or Song,</hi> as Psal. 67, 68, 76, 87, 92.</item>
                           <item>6. <hi>A Song or Psalm,</hi> as Psal. 66, 88, 108.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Of which I will not say, as some Learned men do, that
<list>
                           <item>1. The Voice went before the Instrument, when it is called, <hi>A Song and Psalm,</hi> as Psal. 48.</item>
                           <item>2. The Voice went after the Instrument, when it is called, <hi>A Psalm and Song,</hi> as Psal. 30.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>But this I say, That as we read of Petition, Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, Imprecation, and Deprecation; yet all are comprehended in the word, Prayer. So although there be mention made of Psalms, Hymnes, and spiritual Songs; yet since one and the same is called, <hi>A Psalm or Song; A Song and Psalm,</hi> there is not such diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt them (so far as I can finde) but that in singing <hi>Davids</hi> Psalms, we sing Psalms, Hymnes, and spiritual Songs, and so according to that Scripture <hi>James</hi> 5. 3. <hi>We being merry sing Psalms.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3. The third Objection is a meer Cavil.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. We are to speak to our selves. What then? Not that others may hear us? False. For we are to speak to our selves, <hi>i. e.</hi> to our instruction, namely, amongst our selves. Therefore not only inwardly in our selves, but to the edification of others, of one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And so not only to others, but also to their edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. For in singing we must admonish and sing with Grace, <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 16.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. We are to make melody in our heart. What then? Therefore not with our voice? I wonder at such Collections; much more at such Expressions, what with shoutings? with clamorous noise? For the Apostle enjoyning us to sing with <hi>the heart,</hi> shews with
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:100286:42"/> what affection we are to sing. Not only with the <hi>mouth</hi> or <hi>voice,</hi> but with <hi>heart</hi> and <hi>devotion</hi> also.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. As for making a noise in singing. It must of necessity accompany the same. The <hi>Jews</hi> did often, and were to joyn sound of Musick with their singing, <hi>Psal.</hi> 105. 3, 4, 5. Psaltery and Harpe, <hi>Psal.</hi> 108. 2. Timbrel and Harpe, <hi>Psal.</hi> 98. 5. We are to praise God in the Congregation of the Saints by singing, <hi>Psal.</hi> 149. 1. To have Gods praises in our mouths, <hi>Psal.</hi> 149. 6. To sing with our glory, or our tongue, <hi>Psal.</hi> 108. 1. To sing aloud unto God, and to make a joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full noise, <hi>Psal.</hi> 81. 1. With the voice of a Psalm, <hi>Psal.</hi> 98. 5. And to make a joyful noise with Psalms, <hi>Psal.</hi> 95. 2. The Voice is therefore called, <hi>the daughter of Musick,</hi> Eccl. 12. 4.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. And it passeth my understanding to know, how a man should sing without noise. <hi>Asma</hi> in Greek, <note place="margin">Of <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</note> signifieth, <hi>a Song pronounced with the mouth:</hi> And <hi>Mizmor</hi> in Hebrew, comes of <hi>Zamar,</hi> signifying, <hi>to</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prie dicitur de cantu oris</hi>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <hi>Psallere, de cantu fidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um.</hi> Leigh Sac. Crit.</note>
                        <hi>publish by singing, properly by Instruments;</hi> from whence comes <hi>Zimrah,</hi> signifying, <hi>a verse, a song, and psalmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dical Instruments. Hymnos</hi> (in Greek) <hi>an Hymn,</hi> comes of <hi>Hymne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>; I speak or sing an Hymn; I speak laud and praise.</hi> And the word <hi>Ranan,</hi> signifieth, <hi>to exclaim, to cry out, to shrill out;</hi> for <hi>sorrow,</hi> Lam 2. 19. and for <hi>joy,</hi> Psal. 81. 2. <hi>Rinna,</hi> signifieth, <hi>a Song, and crying out,</hi> Psal. 17. 1. And Peacocks are called in Hebrew <hi>Renanim,</hi> Job 39. 13. for their loud crying. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, signifieth, <hi>I sing, I play on an Instrument;</hi> for <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> is properly spoken of <hi>the sound of strings,</hi> so to strike on them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="66" facs="tcp:100286:43"/>
                     <speaker>Auth.</speaker>
                     <p>You love to hear your self talk. What do you tell us of Harps, and Peacocks, and words we un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand not?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>Your fond Objections enforce me to speak as I have done; and by those words to shew you that sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing implies sound and noise.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plan.</speaker>
                     <p>I pray let us hear what examples you have for <hi>singing of Psalms?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>David</hi> is called, <hi>the sweet Psalmist of Israel,</hi> 2 Sam. 23. 1. There were chief of the Singers; and Songs of praise and thanksgiving unto God, Neh. 12. 46. <hi>I will sing and give praise,</hi> saith <hi>David,</hi> Psal. 108. 1, 3. <hi>I will sing of thy Power, yea I will sing aloud of thy mercy,</hi> Psal. 59. 16. <hi>I will sing and give praise,</hi> Psal. 57. 7.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Auth.</speaker>
                     <p>See, Neighbour, he is in the old Testament again.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, and will be. I had thought you had been satisfied before concerning that. But, I see, Self-love makes men obstinate.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plan.</speaker>
                     <p>I pray Sir, come to the new Testament, and shew examples there, if you can.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, I can, clear and convincing, <hi>Act.</hi> 16. 25. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas,</hi> sang Praises to God.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plan.</speaker>
                     <p>Were they Psalms?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, that they were. The book of Psalms is called in Hebrew, <hi>Sepher Tehillim,</hi> A book of Praises; of <hi>Halal,</hi> to Praise.</p>
                     <p>But to prevent all further cavilling, I will instance in the example of Christ, and his Apostles, singing an Hymne, which was one or more of <hi>David</hi>'s Psalms, wherewith they ended the Paschal Supper, as the <hi>Jews</hi>
                        <pb n="67" facs="tcp:100286:43"/> write. <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ulus Burgensis</hi> affirms that it was a tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Jews,</hi> that when the Pasch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l Lamb was eaten, they did sing, beginning at the 113 Psalm to the 119 exclusively; and this was the Hymne which Christ did sing with his Disc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ples. And D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Lightfoot</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Harm. in new Test. pag. 65.</note> saith, the Hymne that they sang, was Psal. 115. 116, 117, and 118. being the latter part of the <hi>great Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel,</hi> (as they called it.) Which was constantly sung at the Passeover, and the other great Solemnities; and that with this latter part, was this Sol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, it being the practise of the Church to sing it, and that no new one made for this purpos<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> once or any where specified.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Auth.</speaker>
                     <p>Ha, ha, ha; ha, ha, ha; what doth he tell us of <hi>Paul Burges,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Lightfoot?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>Friend, I tell you of Christ, singing a Psalm, and of writers shewing the custom of the <hi>Jews,</hi> singing at their Passeover; to which our Saviour conformes, singing, as the <hi>Jews</hi> called it, <hi>the great Halelujah,</hi> or part of it. And although you scoffe at Writers, yet I I will tell you the practise of the Church from them.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Pliny</hi> (as <hi>Tertullian</hi> reports) who wrote to <hi>Trajan</hi> the Emperour saith, <hi>That by long enquiry he found nothing in the practise of the Christians, but this, that they met together in the night to sing Psalms to Jesus Christ and to God.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And St. <hi>Augustine</hi> writing of himself saith, <hi>That</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>L. H.</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to the Psal.</note>
                        <hi>having forsaken the errors of the</hi> Manichees, <hi>and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced Christianity, coming into the Christian Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, and hearing Psalms sung by the Christians, he could not abstain from weeping, and could not but</hi>
                        <pb n="68" facs="tcp:100286:44"/>
                        <hi>acknowledge the great benefit of this institution.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Must<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>lus</hi> relates of himself, <hi>That when he was at</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>f. in Psal.</note> Augusta, <hi>at the imperial diet,</hi> 1548. <hi>and lived,</hi> as he saith, <hi>in the midst of a strange people, that there was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing did so much affect his soul, and raise up his drouping spirits, and more frequently wring tears from his eyes in gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>at abundance, then the peoples singing of Psalms in the Church, whereby they with heart and tongue praised God.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Bas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>l</hi> in his Pref<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ce to the Psalms is very full in <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, &amp;c.</note> expressing the excellency of the Psalms, saying, <hi>That whereas all the sacred volumes were written by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> of the Holy Spirit, and are profitable as a sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign medicine of the soul; yet—insomuch that by them, the old ulcers of the soul are healed, they that err are reduced into the right way.—Yea, finally, those evill passions, and affections of the minde (which in many respects do tyrannize over the souls of men in this life) are wholly taken away, and that with a certain pleasure and delightful way of leading the minde, for the Spirit of God knowing that mankind is prone to plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, and averse from vertue in respect of the labour that attends it, invites us, desirous to go in the right way, by his holy precepts, expressed in Musical Numbers and measures; that we being allured with the pleasure of our ears, might easily admit and receive the solid pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of the Word.—As a wise Physitian being to give bitter potions to children, to prevent thier nauseating the same, annoints the same with hony; so the pleasures are offered to us being children (not in age, but in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners) in appearance to delight us, but indeed to instruct our souls in the truth.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="69" facs="tcp:100286:44"/>
                     <p> And he adds, <hi>That none ever was so troubled in minde, but so soon as he sings</hi> Psalms <hi>he is pacified, and removes sorrow out of his heart; for—And produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces a most intimate union, and conjunction of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in one Quire, in one spirit—It puts to flight the Devils, it brings the guard of Angels, it is the rest from the labours of the day, the security of nights, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of Infants, the guard of young men, the instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the old men, the ornament of women; in the Wilderness it is a pleasant Inne, it shews to beginners the first principles, to proficients an increase, to the feeble it gives help; furthermore, it graces and adornes pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Solemnities or Festivals; and shews that sorrow which is of God, and extracts tears out of the stony heart.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Answerable St. <hi>Augustine</hi> speaking much in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending <note place="margin">Conf. bo. 10. c. 33.</note> the book of Psalms, and shewing their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency, he saith, <hi>When I remember my tears which I shed at the singing of the Church, in the beginning of my Conversion; and how I am now moved, not with the singing, but the things which are sung, when they are sung with a cleer voice, and a beseeming tune: I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but again acknowledge the great benefit of this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Learned and laborious Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> shews, <hi>That the</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Eccl. Pol. b 5. par. 39.</note>
                        <hi>custom of finging</hi> Psalms, <hi>was in the Church in</hi> Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius <hi>dayes, who suffered under.</hi> Trajan,<hi>—And that it is a thing which</hi> Basil <hi>was perswaded did both strengthen the Meditation of those holy words which were uttered in that sort, and serve also to make attentive, and raise up the hearts of men; a thing whereunto of old, good people did resort, with hope and thirst that thereby espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially</hi>
                        <pb n="70" facs="tcp:100286:45"/>
                        <hi>their souls might be edified; a thing which filleth the minde with comfort and heavenly del<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ght, stirreth up flagrant desires, and affections correspondent unto that which the words contain, allayeth all kinde of base and earthly cogitations, banish<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>th and driveth away those evil secret suggestions, which our inv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>sible enemy is alwayes apt to minister; watereth the heart, to the end it may fructifie; maketh the virtuous in trouble, full of magnanimity and courage; serveth as a most appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved remedy aga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nst all doleful and heavy accidents which befal men in this present life,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>And let me tell you that an honorable Author af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>L. H.</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to the Psal.</note>
                        <hi>That one</hi> Hippolytus <hi>speaking of the end of the World, saith, That in the dayes of Antichrist, singing of Psalms shall cease.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plan.</speaker>
                     <p>You told us, I think, of benefits belonging to such who sing Psalms, did you not?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>I did, and will name some.</p>
                     <p n="1">I. <hi>This pleaseth the Lord better then Sacrifice,</hi> Psal. 69. 30, 31.</p>
                     <p n="2">II. <hi>It is a good thing to sing praises to God,</hi> Psal. 92. 1, 2.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. It was so good a duty that some were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in that work day and night, 1 Chr. 9. 33.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. It is good to us in this time of the Gospel, and that in Prosperity and Adversity. Singing is use<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full when we are merry, to turn the course of our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, into a Religious Channel, and to beget spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual mirth. In mourning, directing our sadness. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> therefore sang in Prison.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. It is good in Prosperity, leading us to true de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, and the rejoycing of Gods people; and being a
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:100286:45"/> means to procure to our selves a sanctified use of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperity, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5. 13.</p>
                     <p>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. We being thereby more stirred to thankfulness for the same.</item>
                           <item>2. We being more fervent in Prayer, and Prayses.</item>
                           <item>3. And thereby more affected with holy du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. It is good in Adversity. This being a soveraign salve against heaviness of heart. Psal. 57. 4. <hi>My soul is among Lyons.</hi> Ver. 7. <hi>I will sing and give praise.</hi> Act. 16. 25. The Apostle in the inward Prison, loaded with stripes, did sing praises to God. Singing therefore stirs up mens spirits, and breeds cheerfulness in holy duties.</p>
                     <p>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. Singing of Psalms is most proper to such who are merry, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5. 13.</item>
                           <item>2. Yet it befits also a sorrowful condition.
<list>
                                 <item>1. For the bearing of present Afflictions, Act. 16. 25.</item>
                                 <item>2. For the remembrance of sins past, as we see in the Penitential Psalms, and Psalm 102.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">III. <hi>Joy is a fruit of the Spirit within,</hi> Gal. 5. 22. Which is expressed no way better, then by singing of Psalms to God. <hi>Luke</hi> 1. 46, 47. <hi>Ephes.</hi> 5. 19. Which places shew, That spiritual joy, is one spiritual fruit of being filled with the Spirit: and that one pious expression of the same joy, is singing of Psalms.</p>
                     <p n="4">IV. Singing of Psalms to God, corresponds for matter, although not in measure, with the Saints con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:100286:46"/> practise in heaven, which is, to sing Halelujah to the great God.</p>
                     <p n="5">V. It differenceth betwixt the Songs of the Godly and the Wicked. <q rend="margQuotes">Theirs being wanton, these of the godly spiritual. St. <hi>Chrysostome</hi> on Psal. 42. saith, Our nature is so delighted with Musick, that sucking-chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, if they weep and are troubled, by that means are brought to rest; Nurses who carry them in their arms going about, &amp; singing certain childish songs, do bring them to sleep. Travellers do ease their journies with pleasant Songs. Husbandmen doing their business often sing. Mariners enforcing the Oares, do so. Women spinning often alone, often sing together. Thus Women, Mariners, Travellers, and Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men do; willing to ease their labour with singing, which is incurred by their work.—Therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause this kind of delight is so agreeable to our souls, lest the Devil by bringing in lascivious and whoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish Ballads, might overturn all; the Lord hath op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed Psalms, that from thence delight and profit may be obtained. For from those external Songs, losse, destruction, and many evils are brought in. But from these spiritual Psalms, much gain, much profit, evidence, sanctification,—and the holy Ghost doth flee speedily into the soul of the singer. And as where there is myre, thither the Swine run; where there are spices, and perfumes, there the Bees inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite: so where there are wanton Songs, thither the the Devils are gathered; but where there are Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, thither the grace of God doth hasten, and san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie the mouth and soul. These things I say, not that you should only commend, but that you should
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:100286:46"/> teach your Sons, and Wives to sing such Songs; not only in spinning and at other works, but chiefly at the Table. For since the Devil doth most of all lie in wait at Banquets, therefore it behoveth before, and at the table, to fortifie a mans self by the help of Psalms, and rising from Feasting to sing Sacred H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>mns to God, with Wife and Childr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>n—As they who bring in Jesters, D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ncers, and Harlots into Feasts, invite thither the Devil, and fill their houses with innumerable conflict<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>: So they who call in <hi>David</hi> with his harp, by him do take in Christ; and where Christ is, there no Devil dare enter.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p n="6">VI. The book of Psa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ms (so called by the Greek Interpreters, because they were Songs to which was joyned the harmony of Instruments) are called by the Hebrews <hi>Praises,</hi> and were to be sung in the Temple, at the hours of sacrifices, as well Quotidian as Solemn. In which Psalms,
<list>
                           <item>I. God speaks,
<list>
                                 <item>1. To his Church by Instructions, Exhortations, Corrections, Consolations, Promises, and Prop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>esies.</item>
                                 <item>2. To his enemies by Threats, Reprofs, and reclaiming them from their rage.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>II. Or the Church speaks to God, or to the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.
<list>
                                 <item>1. To God in Confessions, Complaints, Promises, Praye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>s, and Thanksgivings.</item>
                                 <item>2. To the faithful in Instructions, Exhortations, Corrections, and reprehensions.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>And all this,</p>
                     <p n="1">1. To instruct the faithful in the way of life: which
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:100286:47"/> is to glorifie God with an heart ravished with joy.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. To keep the soul in a lively and spiritual exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise, and application of the Doctrine of Piety, in the fruition of Gods grace: and in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of the holy Ghost.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. And to cause it to feel the joyes of the age to come; and to tast the happiness of it, by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain heavenly motions, to which the soul is driven, and drawn by the use of Psalms, pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctised in fervour of spirit, and purity of mind, as by a very strong and divine engine.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Auth.</speaker>
                     <p>You think you have spoken Clerk-like. As if the reading of the Psalms, may not do as much good, as your singing.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>Whether I have spoken Clerk-like, or you Clown-like, let our Neighbour judge. I love to speak Christian-like, and according to Scripture, which war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants what I have said.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plan.</speaker>
                     <p>But, good Sir, hath singing of Psalms, any use, more or above reading, or common pronun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>Certainly yes; for
<list>
                           <item>1. Singing brings a certain sweet delight to pious ears, <hi>Psal.</hi> 104. 33, 34.</item>
                           <item>2. It occasions a more distinct and fixed Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>al.</hi> 104. 34.</item>
                           <item>3. It hath a more copious and ample profession of Piety, <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 16. <hi>Teaching and admonishing.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>4. And it hath a greater communion of mutual edification, when it is with others, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 19.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="75" facs="tcp:100286:47"/>
                     <speaker>Auth.</speaker>
                     <p>Neighbour, hear all he can say; urge him to shew the directions given by the holy Ghost, to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served in singing.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>A little urging may cause fire to ascend; or, one willing to be doing.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plan.</speaker>
                     <p>I pray Sir, let me hear what rules the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture doth prescribe to be observed in singing.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d.</speaker>
                     <p>With heart and good will. We are to sing,</p>
                     <p n="1">1. To the Lord, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 19. <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 16. Namely not to please men, but as in the presence of God. So to the honour, praise, and glory of God; not for vain glory. That as <hi>of him, and through him, and for him, are all things;</hi> so <hi>to him may be glory for ever,</hi> Rom. 11. 36.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. With grace, <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 16. Namely,
<list>
                           <item>1. By the grace of the Spirit; without which we cannot sing to the Lord.</item>
                           <item>2. So sing, as to praise God, for his benefits in singing, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 15, 16.</item>
                           <item>3. So as to evidence the truth of grace in our souls. And to stir up, exercise, and increase Gods graces in our selves and others.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3. With the heart, <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 16. namely our hearts consenting, to avo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d hypocrisie. So that our singing must not be an outward sound of the mouth, but with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ffection of the heart; it being rightly affected with what we sing.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. We must sing with the Spirit, <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 16. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 19. <hi>Spiritual songs.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 15. <hi>With the spirit:</hi> to stir up spiritual joy.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. And with understanding, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 15. So that our and others understandings may be instructed, and edified.</p>
                     <pb n="76" facs="tcp:100286:48"/>
                     <p> Thus, Neighbour, you see, that for singing of Psalms we have precept and practise in Scripture to warrant and perswade unto it. We have profitable inducements to allure, and rules prescribed for singing, to direct us in this so Sacred Duty. Methinks therefore men should much blame themselves, once to scruple or question a duty so much mentioned in the Word, and so lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>g con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in the Church of God; and by the best and holyest Divines and others, Preachers and Professors, in private and publick.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h.</speaker>
                     <p>Neighbour <hi>Planaes,</hi> you have heard him. Now let me shew what I can, against singing of Psalms.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>Away, away, fond fellow, hear what thou canst say against singing of Psalms; as much to say, as, what thou ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>st say against Scripture!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plan.</speaker>
                     <p>Yet, good S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r, hear him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>Friend, it is dangerous questioning such cleer truths, and duties tending so much to the furtherance of Piety and Devotion. Some men question the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, until they omit those Sacred signes t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> present, seales to confirm, and means to convey Christ and his benefits. Some men question so much ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ut Prayer, whether thus or so, whether without the Spirit, until they pray not at all. Some men question whether they should hear men ordained, or with such company, and in the end hear none at all. <hi>Eve</hi> would be questioning Gods truth, until she smarted for the same, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. For my part, I wonder that men who read or hear the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, cannot see the lawfulness of singing of Psalms. A duty so cleer, that godly Divines give directions how
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:100286:48"/> to Sing aright, taking it for granted that none can que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion the thing it self.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Auth.</speaker>
                     <p>I do more then question it, for I condemn it as unlawful. And I callenge you to dispute with you. And, Neighbour, I warrant you, I'le nonplus and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou dispute, who know'st not one letter in a book? Dost thou know what it is to dispute? I am sure thou do'st not. Yet thou wilt confute me and Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture too, in thy conceipt, rather then part with thine errors. Thy name is <hi>Self-conceit;</hi> Nonsense will be thy weapons, and Obstinacy thy strength.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plan.</speaker>
                     <p>Yet let me intreat so much favour of you, as to hear what he can say.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>For your satisfaction I am content.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plan.</speaker>
                     <p>Neighbour <hi>Authadaes,</hi> speak your mind, shew your grounds against singing of Psalms. Do not ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble about, but observe this order, If you have any Scriptures against singing, alledge them; then if you have any reasons, shew the same.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Auth.</speaker>
                     <p>I will follow your directions, and do affirm, that <hi>Singing of Psalms</hi> is unlawful from Scripture, <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 16. which place shews, that the Songs which Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians are to sing, are <hi>spiritual Songs.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>Who contradicts this? what would you infer hence?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Auth.</speaker>
                     <p>Therefore we are not to Sing with our mouths.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>Is that your meaning? I then answer, They are called <hi>Spiritual,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="1">1. Because the matter of them is spiritual.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. And because although they are sung outwardly
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:100286:49"/> with the mouth: yet they were to be <hi>sung spiritually,</hi> with a <hi>spiritual mind and aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ction to the Lord;</hi> that by such <hi>Songs</hi> and <hi>Singing,</hi> spiritual Devotion might he furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. For the <hi>praising of God</hi> with the mouth, is not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to the praisers, if it be without that of the heart and spirit. What is this against <hi>singing?</hi> I cannot think it sense to say, <hi>Sing inwardly;</hi> for although <hi>joy</hi> is <hi>inward, singing</hi> is an <hi>outward expression</hi> of that <hi>inward joy,</hi> Jam. 5. 13.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Auth.</speaker>
                     <p>Eph: 5. 19. We are <hi>to sing to the Lord in our hearts.</hi> Here is no mention of any voice.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>Yet here is a command to <hi>sing,</hi> which implyes the voice. The words shew, That the attention of the heart is required, and a right intention, Gods honour. And therefore, with <hi>Hierom,</hi> we reprehend them who <hi>sing</hi> for <hi>ostentation,</hi> and only for <hi>carnal delight,</hi> not to stir up Devotion. And with St. <hi>Augustine,</hi> such who do <hi>sing with their mouths, yet have their hearts mute.</hi> Yet the inward part must not exclude the outward, since the lively voice doth not only give vent to affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, but increaseth them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Auth.</speaker>
                     <p>1 Cor. 14. 26. <hi>Every one of you hath a Psalm.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>What then?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aud.</speaker>
                     <p>Therefore we are not to <hi>sing</hi> those <hi>set Psalms,</hi> but use those the Apostle doth mention.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>Do you know what the Apostle meaneth, when he saith, <hi>Every one hath a Psalm?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Auth.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, I warrant you, He means any <hi>inward praising of God.</hi> And so, and no otherwise, we are to <hi>sing.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="79" facs="tcp:100286:49"/>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p n="1">1. It is not true which you say, That <hi>any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward praising of God,</hi> is <hi>singing of Psalms.</hi> For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though all <hi>singing of Psalms</hi> should be to <hi>Gods glory:</hi> yet God is many other wayes <hi>pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>d</hi> and <hi>glorified,</hi> both in <hi>heart,</hi> in <hi>word,</hi> and in <hi>me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s conv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>rsations.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. Concerning the words objected, they are too obscure for you to unfold.</p>
                     <p>They note out,</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Either some <hi>spiritual Songs</hi> dictated and inspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the holy Ghost, which was a thing frequent in the primitive Church, as <hi>the guift of Tongues, Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> &amp;c. If so, I answer:
<list>
                           <item>1. That the extraordinary did not hinder or take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the ordinary means of honouring God.</item>
                           <item>2. If you have such a Psalm now, let us hear it; or, if ever you had, let us know it.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. Or, the words are meant of the Scripture-Psalms already penned; as if the Apostle should say, <hi>Every one of you hath a Psalm;</hi> i. e. <hi>the understanding of a Psalm,</hi> or, <hi>doth praise God with a Psalm.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3. Scripture-Psalms are to be sung
<list>
                           <item>1. For where the word limits not, we are not to make restraint.</item>
                           <item>2. They are part of the Word, full of Comfort, Instruction, and praysing of God, the end of singing.</item>
                           <item>3. Christ himself did sing Scripture-Psalms, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26. 30.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Auth.</speaker>
                     <p>1 Cor. 14. 15. <hi>Sing with understanding.</hi> Prophane persons and Children joyn with you in singing, who neither do nor can sing with under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="80" facs="tcp:100286:50"/>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Praise is comly for the upright,</hi> Psal. 33. 1. yet obligatory to all mankind. We may not disc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ntinue our acts of obedience, because wicked men are in some sort mindful of theirs: men may as well refuse to hear or pray with them. We are to <hi>pray with faith,</hi> Jam. 1. 6. and <hi>hear with faith,</hi> Heb. 4. 2. May we not joyn with the Congregation in hearing and praying, because many are there hearing and praying without faith? If so, farewel all duties with any other. For who knows what is in man, and whether such who joyn with us, fail not in the manner?</p>
                     <p n="2">2. The words are a direction how to sing therefore a commandement of the duty; and no forbidding of the same, in case every one is not so qualified as to sing with understanding.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Concerning children you may consider,</p>
                     <p n="1">1. That <hi>out of the mouths of babes and sucklings</hi> God will <hi>be praised,</hi> Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 21. 16.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. That God commands <hi>children to be taught,</hi> Deut. 6. 7. Prov. 22. 6. Shall we contradict and say, No teaching of them to pray, to sing, to obey; for they cannot do such things with understanding? or rather say, Such are to learn to hear, to sing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that in time by so doing, they may do them as they ought, <hi>with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Auth.</speaker>
                     <p>Ob. Rev. 5. 9. We are to sing <hi>new songs;</hi> the Psalms of <hi>David</hi> are not <hi>new.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>Y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s, they are new.</p>
                     <p>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. When they are sung with such fervency as new things used to be sung.</item>
                           <item>2. They are alway<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>s new, according to Gods grace which never waxeth old.</item>
                           <pb n="81" facs="tcp:100286:50"/>
                           <item> 3. Or, they are new, being sung by the motion of the new spirit of Grace, which doth not so much look after the old benefits of Creation, as after the new benefit of Redemption in Christ, which reneweth all things.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Auth.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi> 4. 24. We must worship God <hi>in spirit and truth.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>The true worshippers of God, yield him a service befitting his Nature; namely, sincere and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right; but this excludes not bodily worship, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 20. For we are to pray and praise God with our <hi>tongues, Jam.</hi> 3. 9. <hi>Psal.</hi> 108. 1. <hi>Sing my glory,</hi> i. e. <hi>tongue,</hi> the glory of man, and means by which man doth outwardly glorifie God. And the external praise of the mouth availes to stir up the inward affection of him, that doth praise, and is a means to stir up others to praise God.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Auth.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Deut.</hi> 4. 2. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 18, 19. We may not <hi>add to,</hi> or <hi>take from, the Word;</hi> therefore not sing Psalms in Meter, that not being the Word of God.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p n="1">1. To add to the Word of God, is I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse:
<list>
                           <item>1. Needlesse: that being alsufficient rule of it self; yea perfect and absolute, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 16. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 16.</item>
                           <item>2. Fruitlesse: because whatsoever is added is vanity, <hi>Isa.</hi> 8. 20.</item>
                           <item>3. Shameful: condemning God of weaknesse and want of Wisdom; equalling or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring mans wisdom above Gods.</item>
                           <pb n="82" facs="tcp:100286:51"/>
                           <item> 4. Hurtful: as Water to Wine, Silver to Gold.</item>
                           <item>5. Dangerous, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 8.</item>
                           <item>6. Therefore Faithless, so Graceless.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. But the turning the Psalms out of <hi>Hebrew</hi> into <hi>English,</hi> out of Prose into Verse, is not an adding or taking away: no more then Preaching upon a Text, so long as the sense and meaning is kept; for those Scriptures speak not of the syllables, or the manner of delivering, but of the sense and meaning. As <hi>Luther</hi> saith well, <hi>To teach the same thing in other words, or more, is not to add.</hi> The Translations therefore, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions, and turning Psalms into Meter, being a teaching of the same things in words fitted for our understandings, are not an adding or taking away, no more then Preaching upon a Text.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. And admit, there are some words, and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain phrases, not so proper as some could wish; nor thought so fit for our changing language, which often varies: what are they to the Duty? or, Can such prove Singing unlawful?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Auth.</speaker>
                     <p>Galat. 5. 1. We must <hi>stand fast in our Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>To infer hence, we must not sing Psalms, is weak and ridiculous.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. For we are <hi>delivered to serve God,</hi> Luk. 1. 74. and <hi>bought with a price to glorifie God,</hi> 1 Cor. 6. 20.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. This is a part of our Christian Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; it being one of the happinesses of Gods <hi>Redeemed,</hi> Revel. 14. 3. and doing this
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:100286:51"/> rightly, we imitate them while we live here.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Auth.</speaker>
                     <p>I will now shew for what Reasons I think singing of Psalms unlawful. 1. Because the praise of the heart being better then that of the mouth, is hindered by it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p n="1">1. Mental prayer is lawful, yet Vocal is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten needful to further affection in Prayer. Why may not the voice also further affection in Praysing God.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Such who use singing meerly for delight, may have their minde taken off from consideration of what they sing. But such who sing for Devotion, do by singing more attend to the things which are said.
<list>
                           <item n="1">1. Because they stay longer on that which is said.</item>
                           <item n="2">2. And because all the affections of our spirit, in regard of their diversity, have their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and peculiar means in the voice and sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to be stirred up by a certain hidden fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarity.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3. There is the same reason in Hearers; amongst whom, although some do not understand what is sung; yet they understand for what it is sung, namely, the glory of God, and that will stirr them up to Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Auth.</speaker>
                     <p n="2">2. Because there are many Imprecations in the Psalms, as <hi>Psal.</hi> 52, 59, 69. and, What warrant have we to Curse? to sing, <hi>Pour out thy wrath as hot as fire,</hi> &amp;c?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="84" facs="tcp:100286:52"/>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p n="1">1. There are divers other Psalms which are not so.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. How may we read them, if we may not sing them?</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Tis a folly to think, that what we sing must ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly suit with our case; we may as well say, what we read should so suit.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. We do not sort Imprecations to our case; as to wish the like judgements on our private Adversaries: But to think of the horrible judgements of God upon unbelievers.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. We may both read and sing these Psalms: pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided,
<list>
                           <item n="1">1. That by occasion of such Imprecations we be stirred up with fear and trembling, to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate upon the horrible judgements of God upon impenitent persons.</item>
                           <item n="2">2. That from thence we profit in Patience and Consolation against Temptations which are wont to arise from the prosperity of the wicked, and miseries of the godly.</item>
                           <item n="3">3. That we indefinitely use them against the enemies of God and of his Church, we being perswaded, there are alwayes some such. But we may not apply them particularly against any; no not our owne, or any mans ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</item>
                           <item n="4">4. That we use them as Prophetical sentences of the holy Ghost, pronouncing the last Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Destruction upon impenitent sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:100286:52"/> who oppose themselves against Gods Kingdom.</item>
                           <item n="5">5. That we use them against our spiritual ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, as the Flesh, the Devil, his Angels, and the World.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Auth.</speaker>
                     <p n="3">3. Because the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ok of Psalms was penned for the state of the <hi>Jews,</hi> the Church then. The hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stories in them did belong to other times and places. How can we now sing them? How can we now say, <hi>By the rivers of Babylon?</hi> &amp;c. <hi>They parted my gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p n="1">1. Singing of Psalms is a moral duty, a part of moral worship, being sorted with other duties which are of a perpetual and immutable obligation. The <hi>Word, Prayer,</hi> and <hi>Singing,</hi> are joyned together, as of equal necessity, <hi>Psal.</hi> 95.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. The Church of God, in all ages, consists of a number of Believers. The faith is one in Christ, all apprehend the Promises to be alike to one another, in Grace, Meditations, in Dispositions, in Aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ctions, in Desires, in Spiritual wants, in the use of Afflictions, in Conversation of life, in performance of duties to God and man; therefore the same Duties, Prayses, Meditations, are now as fit for the Church, and are said, and sung, with the same use and profit as then.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. If we so meditate on them, that we draw from thence spirituall comfort and hope.</p>
                     <p n="2">
                        <pb n="86" facs="tcp:100286:53"/> 2. For which end we are to put upon our selves the persons,
<list>
                           <item n="1">1. Of those of whom those Psalms are sung.</item>
                           <item n="2">2. Or of those who did sing them, so as to conceive, that whatsoever is spoken there, is in a sort spoken to us. For although we are not in <hi>Babylon</hi> (neither were the Jews alwayes when they sung it) yet we may be in great tribulation.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3. Some Psalms contain sad Narratives of the suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of the Church, and of Christ. Which we sing, not as remonstances of our particular case and state to God: But we use them as an occasion to awaken our meditations at the afflicted state of the Church, or the agonies Christ endured for us.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Auth.</speaker>
                     <p n="4">4. God was praysed with Instruments of Musick, as well as with singing of Psalms. The one, namely, Musical instruments are ceased; therefore so should Vocal, or singing of Psalms cease.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p n="1">1. Instrumentall Musick may still be used in Gods service, for any thing that I know to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; so far forth as it may, doth, and will further edification.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. But admit, that it was only for the time of the <hi>Jewish Paedagogie,</hi> yet it doth not thence follow, that Vocal is to cease; for we are still to do many things which the <hi>Jews</hi> did; amongst the rest this: we ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving express command in the New Testament for
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:100286:53"/> the same; and the practise of Christ and his Apostles to warrant it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Auth.</speaker>
                     <p n="5">5. Whereas <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. 5. all are to prayse God. I have heard that a great B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>shop did forbid you Ministers to sing. It seems then, that singing and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of God are not the same; and that you may not lawfully sing.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p n="1">1. This Bishop was one Pope <hi>Gregory,</hi> and this was a d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>cree of his, in his Decretals, which you mean.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. But in that Decree there is no such thing. The sum of the Decree is this, Because the chiefest means whereby Ministers may stir up people to delight in God, is by Doctrine and Preaching, rather then by Singing; he would not have Ministers of the Word, spend their time about Songs, lest they should be hindered from those greater and weightier Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. And to what purpose do you tell me of a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish Decree?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plan.</speaker>
                     <p>Neighbour <hi>Authades,</hi> I assure you, I am well satified, and resolved in Publique to joyn with the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, and to sing at home with my Family as I have done. What say you?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Auth.</speaker>
                     <p>You know I am no Schollar, he may be a little too hard for me in talking: but when I come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst my companions, I suppose they would shew
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:100286:54"/> me (could I but remember) the weakness of his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons and Answers: untill then, I know not what to say.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>Friends, Take heed of those who <hi>cause Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>visions and Offences contrary to the doctrine which you have learned, and avoid them,</hi> Rom. 16. 17. Quarrel not against, nor question duties enjoyned in Scripture: therefore let us all rejoyce in the Lord, <hi>singing new songs,</hi> Psal. 33. 2, 3. <hi>Singing praises with und<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>rstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> Psal. 47. 7. <hi>Let us make a joyful n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ise to God,</hi> Psal. 66. 1. <hi>Praysing the name of God with a song,</hi> Psal. 69. 30. <hi>Let us sing unto the Lord, and make a joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full noise,</hi> Psal. 95. 1, 2. <hi>Make a joyful noise unto the Lord, make a loud noise, rejoyce and sing praise,</hi> Psal. 98. 4. <hi>Let us sing unto him, sing Psalms unto him,</hi> Psal. 105. 2. <hi>It being good to sing prayses to our God, it being pleasant and com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ly,</hi> Psal. 147. 1. <hi>Sing we his prayse in the Congregation of Saints,</hi> Psal. 149. 1. <hi>and in his Sanctuary,</hi> Psal. 150. 1. <hi>Yea let his S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>atutes be our Songs in the houses of our Pilgrimages,</hi> Psal. 119. 54. <hi>For our lips will utter praise, when the Lord hath taught us his Statutes,</hi> Psal. 119. 171. Thus doing, fear not <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>izing;</hi> since so doing we im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tate Gods people, and our blessed Saviour, and obey God. Rather not doing thus fear <hi>Atheism.</hi> What if some Sing not aright; neither do all Hear, Read, or Pray aright, shall we therefore do none of these? And do not think it sufficient to cavil and say, Did the Apostles bid us to sing such Psalms as ours? For it is ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>dent we are commanded to <hi>Sing,</hi> and <hi>Psalms</hi> also; therefore such which we sing. If not,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:100286:54"/> shew what other? yea, what can we sing better then such sacred Songs, which are dictated by God himself, for all manner of Occasions? Sing we then with the heart to the Lord, that hereafter we may in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly quire of Saints and Angels, sing Halelujahs to the Lord our God.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plan.</speaker>
                     <p>Mr. <hi>Hodaegos,</hi> I thank you, and bless God for this our meeting, hoping my Neighbour will consider better with himself, and alter his mind as I have done.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Auth.</speaker>
                     <p>I will promise nothing, but better to think of it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Consider what I have said, and the Lord give you understanding in all things.</hi> Neighbours, Farewel.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:100286:55"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:100286:55"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Catalogue of some Books Printed for</hi> William Tompson <hi>Bookseller in</hi> Harborough.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>MIscellanea;</hi> or, Serious, useful Considerations Moral, Historical, and Theological: together with, the Characters of a True Believer: by <hi>Thomas Goddard,</hi> Gent.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Quarto.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Quakers Apostafie from the perfect rule of the Scriptures, discovered; wherein their Deceits, Blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and Reproaches against Scripture, Autho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ity, and Ordinances are spoken unto and confuted: by <hi>John Timson.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Quarto.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Bar to Free Admission to the Lords Supper Removed; or, a Vindication of Mr. <hi>Humphrey's</hi> Free Admission to the Sacrament of the Lords Supper: by the same Author.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Octavo.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>To receive the Lords Supper, the actuall Right and Duty of all Church Members of years, not Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated, made good against Mr. <hi>Collings</hi> his Exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptions against the Bar Removed: by the same Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Large Octavo.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:100286:56"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Good Prophets sad and suddain loss; or, A Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Preached at the Funeral of Mris. <hi>Dorothy Hornby,</hi> the Wife of Mr. <hi>Walter Hornby:</hi> by Mr. <hi>Samuel Answorth.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Quarto.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>: or, a Vindication of a Regulated Inclosure. As also that those evils which do too usually accompany Inclosure of Commons, are not the faults of Inclosure, but of some Inclosers only: by <hi>Joseph Lee</hi> Minister of the Gospel.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Quarto.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>A Vindication of the Considerations concerning Common-fields and Inclosures: or, A Rejoynder un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that Reply which Mr. <hi>Moore</hi> hath pretended to make unto those Considerations.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Quarto.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Consent and dissent of the <hi>Lutherans</hi> and <hi>Calvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nists</hi> (commonly so called.) With excellent directions for their Brotherly agreement. First written in the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> language, by that Reverend and Famous Divine, Dr. <hi>Johannes Bergius,</hi> Preacher to the most Illustrious Elector of <hi>Brandenburg.</hi> Translated into <hi>English</hi> by <hi>Mauritius Bohemus,</hi> Minister of the Gospel.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Octavo.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>A Brief Explication of Christian Religion; contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning an Exposition of the Apostles Creed, the Ten Commandements, the Lords Prayer, and the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Wherein the Ignorant are taught the Saving Knowledge of God, and of themselves.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Octavo.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:100286:56"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>